<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A key to the art of letters, or, English a learned language, full of art, elegancy and variety being an essay to enable both foreiners, and the English youth of either sex, to speak and write the English tongue well and learnedly, according to the exactest rules of grammar, after which they may attain to Latin, French, or any other forein language in a short time ... : with a preface shewing the necessity of a vernacular grammar ... / by A. Lane ...</title>
            <author>Lane, A. (Archibald)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12675213</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12675213</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65531</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 360:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A key to the art of letters, or, English a learned language, full of art, elegancy and variety being an essay to enable both foreiners, and the English youth of either sex, to speak and write the English tongue well and learnedly, according to the exactest rules of grammar, after which they may attain to Latin, French, or any other forein language in a short time ... : with a preface shewing the necessity of a vernacular grammar ... / by A. Lane ...</title>
                  <author>Lane, A. (Archibald)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xx, 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. and J. Churchil ... and J. Wild ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. xx.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65531:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65531:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A KEY TO THE ART of LETTERS: OR, <hi>Engliſh a Learned Language,</hi> Full of <hi>Art, Elegancy</hi> and <hi>Variety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being an Eſſay to enable both Forei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Youth of either Sex, to ſpeak and write the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue well and learnedly, according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteſt Rules of <hi>Grammar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which they may attain to <hi>Latin, French,</hi> or any other Forein Language in a ſhort time, with very little trouble to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or their Teachers.</p>
            <p>With a PREFACE ſhewing the Neceſſity of a <hi>Vernacular Grammar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dedicated to his Highneſs the Duke of</hi> Gloceſter.</p>
            <p>By <hi>A. LANE,</hi> M.A. late Maſter of the Free-School of <hi>Leominſter</hi> in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> now Teacher of a private School at <hi>Mile-end-green</hi> near <hi>Stepney.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>J. Churchil</hi> at the Black Swan in <hi>Pater-noſter Row,</hi> and <hi>J. Wild</hi> at the Elephant at <hi>Charingcroſs.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:65531:2"/>
            <p>We have read over this Book, intituled, <hi>A Key to the Art of Letters,</hi> and do think it contains many Excellent Rules and Obſervations very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be followed by all who deſire to learn, pronounce, and write the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue exactly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Matthew Shortyng</hi> D. D. Maſter of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Taylors School, <hi>London.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Walker</hi> L. L. D. Maſter of the Charterhouſe School, <hi>London.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Samuel Mountfort</hi> M. A. Maſter of the Grammar-School in Chriſt's-Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, <hi>London.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Richardſon</hi> M. A. Maſter of the Free-School of St. <hi>Martins Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:65531:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Illuſtrious PRINCE WILLIAM Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Highneſs;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Deſign of theſe few Sheets being to ſhow the excellency and uſefulneſs of the <hi>Engliſh Tongue,</hi> I humbly conceiv'd they could not be more properly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd to any than to Your Highneſs, whoſe Intereſt and Concern in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Dignity of Your Native Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, is much greater than of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whomſoever.</p>
            <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:65531:3"/>
            <p>And I hope I have made it appear, beyond contradiction, in this Eſſay, that the <hi>Engliſh Tongue</hi> is as capable of all the Art and Elegancies of <hi>Grammar</hi> and <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> as <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latin,</hi> or any other Language in the World, whether Antient or Modern: and if ſo, it ſeems to be contrary to Senſe and Reaſon, as well as to Antiquity, to put <hi>Engliſh Youth</hi> to toil in any Forein Tongue whatever for the attainment of good Learning, while their own Excellent Language lies neglected and uncultivated, as bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, and unfit for the entertainment of the Liberal Arts and Sciences.</p>
            <p>If we poliſh and adorn our Native Language with good Literature, as the Antients always did theirs, then it will cultivate and accompliſh us more than all the Forein Languages in the World can do: Nor will this be any hindrance to the learning of Forein Tongues, but on the contrary be the moſt effectual means of acquiring them ſpeedily and eaſily that can be imagined.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Literature was in his Mother-Tongue, and perhaps he knew no other; yet King <hi>Philip</hi> did ſo much
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:65531:3"/>admire him for his great Learning, that he writ to him in theſe words: <hi>I thank the Gods, not ſo much on the account that a Son is born to me, as that it is his good hap to be born in thy Life-time; for I hope that after he is perfectly inſtructed by thee, he may be worthy of us, and of ſo great a Kingdom.</hi> And <hi>Alexander</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was ſo ſenſible of the ineſtimable benefit of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Vernacular Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he lov'd him no leſs than he did his Father <hi>Philip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is Your Highneſs's great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that You have an <hi>Alexander</hi> and an <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to write after: and may the Great Example of the One excite You to the imitation of thoſe Heroic Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that all Languages are little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to expreſs; and the Learning of the Other fit You, like <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to write Your own Commentaries.</p>
            <p>If theſe ſmall Beginnings of a Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Engliſh</hi> Education, which is ſo much for the Honour and Advantage of all <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, be favourably enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Your Highneſs, and the Nation, the Author will be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to proceed to ſome further
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:65531:4"/>Improvements of what he has begun for the Publick Good. And who knows but the reviving of this piece of the beſt Antiquity has been reſerv'd for Your Highneſs's Times, whoſe great Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, and early Advances in Learning, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſo Great a Conduct, do all concur to raiſe the Hopes and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Nation, that Your Highneſs may (by the Favour of Heaven) prove a moſt Learned and Virtuous Prince, an Ornament to the Royal Family, and a great Bleſſing to Your native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? And that Your Highneſs may eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day more and more increaſe and confirm theſe Hopes to the Joy of all Good Men, is the moſt ardent prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious Prince,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Highneſs's moſt humble, and moſt devoted Servant, <hi>A. Lane.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:65531:4"/>
            <head>The PREFACE, Humbly ſubmitted to the Learned Reader.</head>
            <p>TO write an <hi>Engliſh Grammar</hi> for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Youth,</hi> may ſeem to many, at firſt view, a very ſuperfluous and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous thing; but if the Reader have a little patience, I hope to make it appear to all the World, that it is ſo far from being ſuperfluous, that on the contrary it is the moſt neceſſary, and beſt Expedient to promote all good Learning that ever was thought of ſince the diſſolution of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>The indiſpenſible neceſſity of Grammar makes the conſideration of it of far greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to Mankind, than of any other Art or Science whatever: for <hi>Grammar,</hi> or the Art of Letters, is univerſally neceſſary, and uſeful to all Perſons of whatſoever Quality, Condition or Sex; becauſe it poliſhes and perfects thoſe noble Faculties of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Speech,</hi> by which Men are diſtinguiſhed from Brutes.</p>
            <p>And therefore it hath ever been the great care and concern of all civiliz'd Nations, to found and erect <hi>Grammar Schools,</hi> for the cultivating and improving the Children of both Rich and Poor, that there might be a conſtant ſupply and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Learned Men to ſit at the Helm of Publick Affairs, without whoſe wiſe Conduct no Kingdom or State can be preſerved from Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Miſery: for Men without Learning,
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:65531:5"/>are rather rough-draughts of Men, than Men.</p>
            <p>But alas! this noble Art that ſo much improves and refines humane Underſtanding, and is the Golden Key to unlock all other Liberal Arts and Sciences, and the Gate that gives an eaſy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into all Forein Languages, is it ſelf the hardeſt of all others to be attain'd to; tho not by reaſon of any intrinſick or inſeparable Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty that is in it, but becauſe it is every where miſunderſtood, and conſequently miſapply'd, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the Latin Tongue ceas'd to be a living Language.</p>
            <p>Both Maſters and Scholars in all the <hi>European</hi> Schools, are ſo miſerably toyl'd and perplex'd in teaching and learning <hi>Grammar,</hi> that almoſt all learned and ingenious Perſons ſhun to be School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, but whom neceſſity drives to thoſe Workhouſes for the neceſſary ſubſiſtance of Life. And generally all Children are utterly averſe to go to the Schools, where they find nothing for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years together, but a conſtant Series of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperable Diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>culties, like one Wave upon the back of another, ready to overwhelm their weak Underſtandings: and the reaſon is, becauſe they are forc'd to cleave the Block with the blunt end of the Wedg. Is it any wonder then to ſee ſo much ſweat and pains with ſo little ſucceſs, in all Schools without exception?</p>
            <p>Many of the Nobility and Gentry (whoſe Children need Learning moſt, and in whom it would be moſt beneficial to Mankind) are by reaſon of theſe hardſhips often at a loſs, whether to indulge thoſe pledges of their Love, and hopes of their Families, in an eaſy Ignorance, or to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe their Learning at ſo dear a rate, as the racking and torturing their tender Wits, ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:65531:5"/>their Spirits, and forfeiting, for the moſt part, the eaſineſs and contentment of their Minds, which ought to be the continual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of their younger years.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of theſe Diſtreſſes every where, both upon Maſters and Scholars, has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged the Endeavours of many Learned and Excellent Men of ſeveral Nations to ſtudy, and find out various new Methods, and compoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious new Forms of <hi>Grammar;</hi> but all to little or no purpoſe: for the old difficulties ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue under all their new Methods, like an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the firſt Concoction, that cannot be mended in the ſecond and third.</p>
            <p>The Author, who has been long chain'd to theſe Gallies, and has tugg'd at the Oar for many years, having a Fellow-feeling, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Fellow-ſufferer with his Brethren in this kind of Calamity, is willing, among others, before he go off the Stage of this World, to caſt his Mite into the common Treaſury; which he hopes will contribute more to the eaſe and comfort of his Fellow-labourers, and their Scholars, than any thing that has ever yet been attempted, to alleviate their Bondage, and ſweeten their Lives while they grind in thoſe Mills.</p>
            <p>But yet he would not be miſtaken, as if he thought himſelf any taller than thoſe who went before him; but being very thoughtful in this great and common Concern of Mankind, and ſtanding upon the Shoulders of others, he thinks he has made ſome further Diſcoveries, which he humbly ſubmits to the candor and judgment of the Learned.</p>
            <pb n="x" facs="tcp:65531:6"/>
            <p>He ſays then, that the principal End and Uſe of <hi>Grammar</hi> is univerſally miſtaken by all the <hi>European</hi> Nations, who think it to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but an Inſtrument to acquire ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Tongue: Whereas the true End and Uſe of <hi>Grammar</hi> is to teach us how to ſpeak and write well and learnedly in a Language al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready known, according to the unalterable Rules of right Reaſon, which are the ſame in all Languages how different ſoever they be.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> writ all their Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Books in their Mother-Tongue, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had their <hi>Grammars</hi> in their own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and for that only, and for no other; which made their Application to Learning ſo eaſy and ſucceſsful, that it was as rare to find any of their Youth of either Sex, that were put to School, fail of being Learned, as it is rare for the Youth of the preſent <hi>European</hi> Nations to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ſome little ſmattering of it, after ſeveral years drudgery in the Schools.</p>
            <p>It is not any Language as ſuch, that makes a Perſon Learned: but the Wiſdom and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that is written in that Language, which without the Art of <hi>Grammar</hi> can never be well underſtood. The common People in <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Athens</hi> (tho they could ſpeak <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> from the Cradle) were not one jot more learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than the Vulgar in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>France.</hi> Then if Learning conſiſt not in Sounds, but in Senſe, why may not <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men be as learned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latin,</hi> as the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> were without <hi>Engliſh?</hi> A common Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Soldier may (if his Memory be good) attain to the ſeveral Languages of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trys where he travels; and ſuppoſe among them
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:65531:6"/>
               <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin;</hi> yet without the Art of <hi>Grammar</hi> he is as illiterate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned as before.</p>
            <p>What can we imagine to be the reaſon that ſo few among us, who are not bred Scholars, can neither ſpeak nor write well, nor with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny competent meaſure of underſtanding make uſe of our own <hi>Engliſh</hi> Books? Sure it is not for want of <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latin,</hi> more than of <hi>Welch</hi> or <hi>Iriſh;</hi> for Words are but the Conduit-pipes to convey Senſe and Learning, being in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves neither learned nor unlearned. Here it may be asked, how then it comes to paſs that Scholars can ſpeak, and write with more ſenſe and underſtanding than others? I anſwer, that it is not for having <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latin,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Forein Language, but becauſe they have learned the Art of <hi>Grammar</hi> with thoſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, which yet they might have learned far better, and with much leſs expence of Mony, Time, and Pains, in their Mother-Tongue, as the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Tho, as I ſaid before, the chief end of <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> be not to acquire a Forein Tongue, any more than the Mathematics or any other Art; yet it is of excellent uſe to attain to all Tongues, and all Liberal Arts and Sciences; for he that is a good <hi>Grammarian</hi> in his Mother-Tongue, may, without any Miracle (if his Memory be ſtrong enough) attain to as many Languages as <hi>Mithridates</hi> King of <hi>Pontus,</hi> with little or no pains in any Forein <hi>Grammar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can any thing be imagined more abſurd and ridiculous, than to put Children to learn <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Grammar</hi> at once? To learn an unknown Tongue by an unknown Art, muſt needs be a
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:65531:7"/>Barbarous and <hi>Gothic</hi> Cuſtom; for I am very ſure it is neither <hi>Greek</hi> nor <hi>Roman.</hi> The great <hi>Tully</hi> himſelf would have thought it ſuch a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification to him in the height of his Strength and Wit, that it is more than probable the World had never been bleſt with his excellent and learned Works, had he been obliged to learn <hi>Latin,</hi> after the ſame manner that our poor Children are forced to before they be ten years old.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded that a Youth who is made a good <hi>Grammarian</hi> in his Mother-Tongue, may afterwards (if under good Conduct) read and underſtand all the <hi>Roman</hi> Authors extant, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Proſe or Poetry, in as little or leſs time than another of equal Age and Capacity can be Maſter of <hi>Lilly</hi>'s <hi>Grammar</hi> alone. And that this may not ſeem ſo very ſtrange and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable, let any School-maſter take a Boy that has been perfectly taught the <hi>Grammar</hi> of his Mother Tongue, and put him immediately to a plain <hi>Latin</hi> Author, without ſo much as teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him firſt to decline or conjugate one word in <hi>Latin,</hi> he ſhall learn more in one Month, than another of the ſame Age and Capacity can poſſibly do in a whole quarter of a Year in the common Methods. And ſuppoſe, for inſtance, the firſt Sentence that offers it ſelf be this, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amat filium;</hi> after the Maſter has conſtrued it to him in the natural order, he will tell him as readily as if he had been ſeven years at <hi>Latin,</hi> that <hi>Pater</hi> is a Noun Subſtantive of the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native Caſe, of the Maſculine Gender, and of the Singular Number; that <hi>amat</hi> is a Verb Active Tranſitive of the third Perſon Singular of the Preſent Tenſe, and of the Indicative
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:65531:7"/>Mood; that <hi>filium</hi> is the Accuſative of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject after the Verb Active <hi>amat,</hi> and ſo of any other plain Sentence; and all this in leſs than a quarter of an hour, which many cannot do in the common Methods, after they have been a whole year at the <hi>Latin</hi> School. Nor is it unlikely by this time, that every word in the Sentence has inſenſibly fixt it ſelf in his Memory without his care or concern. Would not ſome weak Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be apt to think that this were Conjuring, or Legerdemain, when it is nothing elſe but the real effect of a rational Education in the Mother-Tongue, which is the true Standard and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all our Attainments in Forein Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges?</p>
            <p>But here ſome will be ready to object, That the many <hi>Idioms,</hi> and burdenſom Exceptions that are in the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, will ſtop the Youth's career, and be a clog at his heels in ſpite of this rational Conduct. To which I anſwer, firſt, That all Languages have their <hi>Idioms,</hi> and anomalous words no leſs than the <hi>Latin;</hi> and therefore that difficulty is not pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue only, more than to <hi>Engliſh</hi> or any other Language. Secondly, That the only way they can be a hindrance to him is (by ſtopping his progreſs in reading Authors) to put him to get by heart, as a particular Task, unconnected and looſe Words, or Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, which like Ropes of Sand, are no ſooner done but undone; or rather like the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyphian</hi> Stone, which tumbles down much faſter than it was roul'd up. But if no words, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Analogous or Anomalous, be minded any where but in the contexture of good Senſe; they will of courſe inſinuate themſelves into the
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:65531:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:65531:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:65531:9"/>Memory by frequent reading, as they do in the Mother-Tongue by frequent converſation.</p>
            <p>We do not put our Children to toil them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Mother-Tongue with a task of words, whether regular or irregular; and yet they equally underſtand them all. And if the Child be ask'd how he came by ſo many words, he can tell you no more than if you ſhould convey ſomething into his Pocket by ſtealth, and then ask him how it came there.</p>
            <p>Thus it has pleaſed God in his Mercy to Mankind, to make the acquiring not only of one, but of ſeveral Languages, ſo eaſy to Children by Converſation, that they never complain of it as any burden, but are rather apt to think it is natural to them; tho that be a miſtake: for he that never heard a word ſpoken, can never ſpeak a word; and therefore thoſe that are born deaf, are perpetually dumb. But if Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were obliged, by ſtated Leſſons, to get their Mother-Tongue alone by heart, they would either pretend to be deaf, or at leaſt wiſh they were ſo, to be freed from thoſe Anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that muſt unavoidably attend them. And tho the acquiring of Language by reading be more laborious and leſs expeditious than by converſation, yet it is next to converſation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a kind of commerce with the dead or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; but there is neither of the two in getting looſe words by heart. By all this it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that oppreſſing the Memory with Forein <hi>Grammars,</hi> and Forein Words in ſet Leſſons, is the next great Impediment of attaining to Learning and Languages.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Impediment that is any thing conſiderable, is the putting Children to
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:65531:9"/>learn <hi>Grammatical</hi> Propoſitions or Rules barely propos'd, without giving any reaſon for what is affirmed: This makes Children ſeem ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid and unlearned (when they chance to be ask'd a Reaſon why the thing is ſo, or ſo) that they cannot endure to be interrogated by any body in their Learning, but uſually withdraw themſelves, or cry, being griev'd and aſham'd of their Ignorance; which yet is neither their own fault nor their Teacher's, but of the bad Tools they have to work by. Young ones are of themſelves very inquiſitive and curious to know the Reaſons of things; and therefore moſt Infants are full of their pretty <hi>whys,</hi> and <hi>wherefores;</hi> which when ſolidly anſwer'd, are both delightful and profitable to them. To remove this Block out of Childrens way, I have given the beſt Reaſons I could for every Propoſition I lay down in my Book: for a bare Affirmation without a Reaſon for it, is rather a parroting Rote than a rational Knowledg; and the more ſenſible any Child is, he takes the greater pleaſure in any thing that has ſome colourable Reaſon ſubjoin'd to it. And beſides, to reaſon a Child into his Learning, greatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances the rational Faculty, which is no leſs improv'd by frequent Reaſoning, than Writing is by frequent Writing, or Singing by frequent Singing: And every body knows that Habits are acquired by repeated Acts; and what ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit more neceſſary than that of Reaſon and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding?</p>
            <p>Let none miſtake me, as if I thought the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Grammar</hi> altogether uſeleſs; for I think it very uſeful, as a Repoſitory, to be often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted in our reading as we do our <hi>Dictiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi>
               <pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:65531:10"/>which I think is the ſureſt way to make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing in it our own; but to oppreſs the Memory by getting ſo much by heart, is ſo far from promoting Learning, that it is a very great hindrance to it: for one Word ſhuffles out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, but one Senſe does not drive out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and therefore Senſe is a more faithful Preſerver of all Words, than an overcharg'd Memory.</p>
            <p>Our young Gentlewomen, who have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally been diſcouraged from good Learning (their more nice and tender Conſtitutions not being able to endure thoſe rugged and thorny Difficulties in the Methods hitherto practiſed) may, if they be not wanting to themſelves, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to a perfect knowledg of the Art of <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> in the method here propoſed, by which they may become as learned as thoſe excellent <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Matrons recorded in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; which will contribute much more to the good of their Children and Families afterward, than all thoſe inferior Attainments which take up ſo much of their beſt time, and which are generally uſeleſs to them in the remaining part of their lives. And if any of them have a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous ambition of underſtanding the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, they may now do it at a much eaſier rate than ſome excellent <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ladies of our own time, who with a maſculine Courage waded through a thouſand Difficulties till they attain'd to a great perfection in all humane Learning, notwithſtanding thoſe Labyrinths and Mazes that lay in their way in the ordinary Method. And if the Author has found out the true Secret of an eaſy and rational Education, that may prove to the advantage of the fair Sex,
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:65531:10"/>who have ſo many Slights and Affronts put upon them for want of Learning, he thinks all his Pains and Labour happily beſtow'd.</p>
            <p>I hope the Learned will forgive me, if I be forc'd to make uſe of ſome terms not uſual in <hi>Grammar,</hi> as <hi>Subject, Predicate, Object,</hi> and ſuch like, which I have not uſed out of vanity, but of neceſſity, either to prevent Circumlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions in terms of Art, or to avoid terms which are vagous or common to ſeveral Arts. If I have borrowed theſe Terms from Logick, I am perſwaded that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed them firſt from <hi>Grammar,</hi> which was in being long before his Logic, which I think (with ſubmiſſion to better Judgments) to be nothing elſe but <hi>Grammar,</hi> except his ſuperad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded invention of Syllogiſms, and ſome other things of leſs uſe, which he ingraſted upon the Stock of <hi>Grammar.</hi> And in my weak opinion the Art of thinking and ſpeaking are not two, but one Art; for <hi>Grammar</hi> firſt teaches us how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of things in the order of Nature, and then how to expreſs our Conceptions by ſpeaking or writing: for we can never ſpeak or write well, what we cannot rightly conceive; Speaking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing elſe but vocal Thoughts, and Thoughts but ſilent Speaking, and Writing the Images or Characters of them both.</p>
            <p>I have choſen the <hi>Socratical</hi> way of Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Anſwer in my Book, as moſt imſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; the frequent Interlocutions making Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſs tedious, and more intelligible to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who are very ſociable Creatures, and love good company in every thing they do.</p>
            <p>I was willing to deliver at the ſame time what belongs to the ſame head, that it might not be
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:65531:11"/>look'd for in two ſeveral places; yet any thing the Teacher thinks more nice or remote from the Child's Capacity at firſt, he may paſs over it <hi>ſicco pede,</hi> till afterwards: for whatever is to be firſt learn'd, is much eaſier and plainer than in the common <hi>Accidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not ſet down ſo many Examples as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe might be uſeful, becauſe I would not diſcourage Children with a bulky Book; but the diſcreet Teacher may ſupply that defect when he finds it needful. And as for thoſe that think to become good <hi>Grammarians</hi> by the Book alone, without a Maſter, they will find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves miſtaken, and loſe their labour: for the Art of <hi>Grammar,</hi> tho in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> is no leſs a Myſtery to the unlearned, than a Mechanick Trade in plainer <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which yet requires a Maſter, and ſeven years Apprenticeſhip.</p>
            <p>This is all I have to ſay, as to the Method of the Book, ſubmitting it in every thing elſe to the favorable Correction of the Learned.</p>
            <p>Now ſince no Language in the World ſeems more capable of having all manner of Learning treaſur'd up in it, than our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue; why may we not, after the laudable Example of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> (beſides our <hi>Latin</hi> Schools) ſet up <hi>Grammar, Rhetoric,</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy</hi> Schools in our Mother-Tongue, that Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiners abroad may covet to learn our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as we do <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> for thoſe Treaſures of Learning and Knowledg that are lock'd up in them? Our Language has (beſides its innate eaſineſs) a peculiar felicity, by which we may incorporate into it whatever uſeful or ſignificant words we find in <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latin,</hi> or any other Forein Language. Thus the cultivat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:65531:11"/>and enriching our Mother-Tongue with all manner of good Literature, would ſoon make our happy Iſland famous for all kind of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Virtue, which would then be eaſily diffus'd into the Minds and Manners of People, having ſuch an eaſy and native Vehicle as the Mother-Tongue. This would be a more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual means to reform the corruption of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo much complain'd of among us, than all the coercive and penal Laws that can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed: for, as Learning and Virtue generally go together, ſo Ignorance and Vice are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Twins; or more properly, Ignorance is the Mother, and Vice the Daughter.</p>
            <p>If thoſe who have Power and Authority in the Nation, were pleas'd to oil the Wheels of a learned Engliſh Education, and put them once in motion, by encouraging Perſons quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to carry on ſuch an excellent Deſign, I am perſwaded we might in a few years have a hundred learned and virtuous Perſons for one we have now. <hi>Britanniam, quam nacti ſumus, hanc ornemus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were we as induſtrious in improving and cultivating our Language, as the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> were, we might equal, if not exceed them, having many Advantages not known in their time. We might have as learned Leaders and Commanders, both by Sea and Land, as they had, who by their Learning, Civility and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in their Mother-Tongue, inlarged their Dominions no leſs than by their Arms: The barbarous Nations being, as it were, ambitious to be conquered by ſuch brave and generous E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, who ſought rather to ſubdue their Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity, and civilize their Manners, than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:65531:12"/>their Perſons, or ruin their Countries. Muſt we ſtill grace their dead Languages with the Title of <hi>Literae humaniores,</hi> and leave our own out, by which we tacitly ſeem to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg our ſelves <hi>Gentem barbaram, aut ſaltem minùs humanam?</hi> And ſince it pleas'd God to convey Chriſtianity into the Iſle of <hi>Great Britain</hi> on the Wings of theſe learned Languages which are now dead, ought not the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Chriſtians, in a grateful ſenſe of ſuch Goodneſs, to poliſh, refine, and enrich their living Language with all excellent Knowledg, were it for no other end but to carry the Chriſtian Religion to other wretched and barbarous Nations, who for want of Learning and Virtue, are but a kind of more ſavage Beaſts?</p>
            <p>To conclude; If no Children were to learn Latin, or any other Forein Language, till they had firſt learn'd the Art of <hi>Grammar</hi> in their Mother-Tongue, I doubt not but our Latin Schools would ſoon become much more ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and uſeful to the Nation than ever yet they have been.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 10. line 23. r. <hi>Diphthong.</hi> P. 11. l. 1. r. <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> P. 12. l. 15, &amp; 24. r. <hi>Additional;</hi> l. 26. r. <hi>the.</hi> P. 22. l. 5. r. <hi>for more;</hi> l. 30. r. <hi>Termination.</hi> P. 24. l. 25. r. <hi>both.</hi> P. 27. l. 24. r. <hi>which.</hi> P. 34. l. 15. r. <hi>formed.</hi> P. 35. l. 25. r. <hi>encreaſed.</hi> P. 39. l. 16. r. <hi>intranſitive.</hi> P. 41. l. 28. r. <hi>requires.</hi> P. 42. l. 17. r. <hi>after.</hi> P. 43. l. 25. r. <hi>Tenſes;</hi> l. 26. r. <hi>The.</hi> P. 46. l. 6. r. <hi>thou.</hi> P. 47. l. 25. r. <hi>Participle.</hi> P. 51. l. 13. r. <hi>been.</hi> P. 56. l. 8. r. <hi>conjugated.</hi> P. 110. l. 16. after <hi>middle</hi> inſert, <hi>they may be in the middle.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="grammar">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65531:12"/>
            <head>A KEY TO THE Art of Letters.</head>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is</hi> Grammar?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. GRammar</hi> is an Art that Teaches the Right Way of <hi>Speaking</hi> and <hi>Writing,</hi> according to the particular Form of every <hi>Language.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Parts of</hi> Grammar <hi>are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There are four Parts of <hi>Grammar; Letters, Syllables, Words,</hi> and <hi>Sentences.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65531:13"/>
               <head>Of the Letters.</head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is a</hi> Letter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A <hi>Letter</hi> is the <hi>Character</hi> or <hi>Mark</hi> of an individual or ſingle <hi>ſound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are the</hi> Letters <hi>diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of their</hi> ſound?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Letters,</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>ſound,</hi> are diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Vowels</hi> and <hi>Conſonants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Vowel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Vowel</hi> is a <hi>Letter</hi> that can be ſounded alone without a <hi>Conſonant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Conſonant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Conſonant</hi> is a <hi>Letter</hi> that cannot be ſounded without a <hi>Vowel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many</hi> Letters <hi>are there in</hi> Engliſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are <hi>Twenty Six Letters</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> viz. a, b, c, d, e, f, g, h, i, j, k, l, m, n, o, p, q, r, s, t, u, v, w, x, y, z.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many of them are</hi> Vowels?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Six of them are <hi>Vowels, viz.</hi> a, e, i, o, u, y, all the reſt are <hi>Conſonants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Conſonants are called <hi>Mutes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Conſonants,</hi> b, c, d, f, g, k, p, t, are called <hi>Mutes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is a</hi> Mute <hi>ſo called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Mute</hi> is ſo called, becauſe a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid</hi> before it cannot be ſounded with it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65531:13"/>in the ſame Syllable with the <hi>Vowel</hi> after it; as, <hi>rpo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Conſonants are called <hi>Liquids?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Conſonants</hi> l, n, r, are called <hi>Liquids.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is a</hi> Liquid <hi>ſo called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Liquid</hi> is ſo called, becauſe a <hi>Mute</hi> before it can be ſounded with it in the ſame Syllable with the <hi>Vowel</hi> after it; as, <hi>pro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not</hi> m <hi>a</hi> Liquid?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. M</hi> is not a <hi>Liquid</hi> becauſe a <hi>Mute</hi> before it cannot, without force, be ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it in the ſame Syllable with the <hi>Vowel</hi> after it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is</hi> h <hi>a</hi> Letter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. H</hi> is a Note of <hi>Aſpiration</hi> or <hi>Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> rather than a <hi>Letter;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Aſpirats, ch, gh, ph, rh, ſh, th,</hi> are but ſingle <hi>Conſonants</hi> expreſs'd by two <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> c <hi>ſounded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The genuine or natural ſound of <hi>c</hi> is hard like <hi>k,</hi> but we always ſound it ſoft like <hi>s</hi> before <hi>e, i</hi> and <hi>y,</hi> as in the words <hi>Centre, Citron, Cypher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> g <hi>ſounded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The genuine ſound of <hi>g</hi> is hard, as in the word <hi>good;</hi> but for the moſt part we ſound it ſoft, like <hi>j,</hi> before <hi>e, i,</hi> and <hi>y;</hi> as in the words <hi>Gentle, Ginger, Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65531:14"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> ti <hi>ſounded before a</hi> Vowel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſound <hi>ti</hi> before a <hi>Vowel,</hi> like <hi>ſi,</hi> as in the word <hi>Relation;</hi> but when <hi>s</hi> or <hi>x</hi> comes before it, or when it is in the firſt or laſt <hi>Syllable</hi> of a word, then <hi>t</hi> keeps its natural ſound; as in the words, <hi>Chriſtian, tied, ſeveritie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> ph <hi>ſounded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ph</hi> is ſounded like <hi>f,</hi> and is uſually written inſtead of <hi>f</hi> in words derived from the <hi>Greek;</hi> as, a <hi>Prophet,</hi> a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> ch <hi>ſounded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſound <hi>ch</hi> in meer <hi>Engliſh</hi> words, as in the word <hi>Check;</hi> but in words bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the <hi>Greek,</hi> we uſually ſound it like <hi>k,</hi> as in the words, <hi>Chriſt, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> w <hi>ſounded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We uſually ſound <hi>w</hi> like the Vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>u,</hi> and for the moſt part we write it inſtead of <hi>u,</hi> in the middle and end of words, as in <hi>Vowel, Law, Bow,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> y <hi>ſounded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When <hi>y</hi> begins a Syllable, we ſound it as in the word <hi>yea,</hi> and then it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Conſonant;</hi> every where elſe it is a <hi>Vowel,</hi> and is ſounded like <hi>i;</hi> and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways written at the end of words inſtead of <hi>i,</hi> as in <hi>my, thy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->† Since different <hi>Sounds</hi> ſhould in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon have different <hi>Names</hi> leading to thoſe <hi>Sounds,</hi> it would be much for the eaſe of <hi>young Scholars</hi> and their <hi>Teachers,</hi> to call c hard, <hi>kee;</hi> c ſoft, <hi>ſee;</hi> g hard; <hi>ghee;</hi> g ſoft, <hi>jee;</hi> ch ſoft, <hi>chee;</hi> ch hard, <hi>ke;</hi> ph, <hi>fee;</hi> ſh, <hi>ſhee;</hi> th <hi>thee;</hi> wh, <hi>whee; y</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant, <hi>yee;</hi> and qu, <hi>quee,</hi> ſince it is but one ſingle <hi>Conſonant</hi> under two <hi>Characters.</hi> And if the <hi>Printers</hi> did alſo diſtinguiſh them by ſome Point, it would make them much more eaſie; for it is a great Oppreſſion of <hi>Children,</hi> to force them, contrary to Reaſon, to give different <hi>ſounds</hi> to the ſame <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,</hi> without the leaſt <hi>mark</hi> of <hi>diſtinction.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65531:14"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Diphthong <hi>or</hi> double Vowel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Diphthong</hi> or <hi>double Vowel,</hi> is two ſingle Vowels ſounded together in one continued Breath.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which are the moſt uſual</hi> Diphthongs <hi>in</hi> Engliſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The moſt uſual <hi>Diphthongs</hi> in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> are theſe thirteen, <hi>ai, ei, oi, au, eu, ou, ee, oo, ea, eo, oa, ie, ui,</hi> as in the words <hi>aid, eight, join, fault, feud, found, feed, food, Meat, People, Boat, piece, build.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note, y</hi> and <hi>w</hi> are often the <hi>ſubjunctive,</hi> or latter Vowels of a <hi>Diphthong,</hi> inſtead of <hi>i</hi> and <hi>u,</hi> eſpecially in the end of words, as <hi>buy, few,</hi> &amp;c.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->† When two <hi>Vowels</hi> that uſually make a <hi>Diphthong</hi> are to be ſounded ſeparately in two diſtinct Syllables, ſome put two Points, called a <hi>Diaereſis,</hi> or Mark of diviſion over the ſubjunctive or latter <hi>Vowel,</hi> as in the word <hi>Creätor.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are the</hi> Letters <hi>diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of their</hi> Form <hi>or</hi> Figure?</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65531:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Letters,</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Figure,</hi> are diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Small.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>Where are the</hi> Great, <hi>or</hi> Capital Letters <hi>uſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Great,</hi> or <hi>Capital Letters</hi> are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed in the beginning of <hi>Words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>What Words begin with</hi> Capitals, <hi>or</hi> Great Letters?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt word of every new Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od; the firſt word of every Verſe; all proper Names, and Adjectives derived of proper Names; all Names or Titles of Honour and Dignity; all Names of Arts, Offices, and Trades; all Emphatical or Remarkable Words begin with <hi>Capitals,</hi> or <hi>Great Letters;</hi> and in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the firſt Perſon ſingular, <hi>I,</hi> is always written by a <hi>Capital.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the ſmall</hi> s <hi>written?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſmall <hi>s</hi> is uſually written long
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65531:15"/>in the beginning and middle of words, and always ſhort in the end, as <hi>Seaſons, Seſſions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Formation of the Letters.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are the Letters diſtinguiſhed, in reſpect of the Organs or Inſtruments of Speech?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Letters, in reſpect of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, or Inſtruments of Speech, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed into <hi>Gutturals, Palatines,</hi> and <hi>Labials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which are the</hi> Gutturals?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Gutturals,</hi> or Throat-Letters are thoſe which are formed by a <hi>ſofter,</hi> or <hi>harder Expreſſion</hi> of the Spirit or Breath out of the Throat, as <hi>c. g, h<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> k.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which are the</hi> Palatines?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Palatines,</hi> or Palate-Letters, are thoſe that are formed by a <hi>ſofter</hi> or <hi>harder Impreſſion</hi> of the Tongue againſt the Palate, whence they are alſo called <hi>Linguals,</hi> or Tongue Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as <hi>d, l, r, s, t.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which are the</hi> Labials?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Labials,</hi> or Lip Letters, are thoſe that are formed by a <hi>ſofter</hi> or <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Compreſſion</hi> of the Lips together, as <hi>b, f, m, p, v.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are the</hi> Vowels <hi>formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the <hi>Vowels</hi> are formed with the Mouth open; the Vowel <hi>a</hi> with a greater
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65531:16"/>opening, all the reſt with a leſſer open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>a</hi> is Guttural, <hi>e</hi> and <hi>i</hi> Palatine, <hi>o</hi> and <hi>u</hi> Labial.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what uſe is it to know how the Letters are formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To know how the Letters are form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is of great uſe;
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1ſt.</hi> to help Children that have any Impediment in their Speech.</item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <hi>2dly.</hi> to know the true Derivation and Compoſition of Words; for the Letters of the ſame Organ being ſo near in ſound, are often put for one another; as <hi>v</hi> for <hi>f,</hi> in <hi>Knives; t</hi> for <hi>d,</hi> in <hi>forc't.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p><!-- NOTE -->† The Letters are called the Elements of Speech, becauſe they are the firſt Principles of which all Speech is compoſed; for Syllables are made of Letters, and Words of Syllables, and Sentences of Words.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Syllables.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Syllable?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Syllable</hi> is a ſound uttered in one Breath, and conſiſts of one ſingle <hi>Vowel,</hi> or <hi>Diphthong,</hi> alone; or with one or more <hi>Conſonants</hi> joyned with it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can there be any</hi> Syllable <hi>without a</hi> Vowel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There can be no <hi>Syllable</hi> without a <hi>Vowel,</hi> becauſe no <hi>Conſonant</hi> can be ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alone.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:65531:16"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many</hi> Syllables <hi>are there in a Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are as many <hi>Syllables</hi> in a word, as it has ſingle <hi>Vowels</hi> or <hi>Diphthongs</hi> in it; except <hi>e</hi> mute at the end of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Words.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->† Since the greateſt difficulty in Reading, Writing, and Spelling <hi>Engliſh</hi> is occaſion'd by the Vowel <hi>e</hi> in the end of many Words, we ſhall ſhew the true uſe of it in the following Queſtions; and for diſtinction ſake, call it <hi>e Servile.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of e Servile.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the uſe of</hi> e Servile?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Servile</hi> is of great uſe in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue; for by its help we can borrow the moſt ſigniſicant and uſeful Words from other Lauguages, to inrich our own; and ſo far diſguiſe and transform them into good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that others cannot lay claim to them as theirs; as for <hi>Example,</hi> theſe Latin words, <hi>Candela, Vinea, Linea, Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Centrum,</hi> are made good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by the help of <hi>e Servile,</hi> thus; a <hi>Candle,</hi> a <hi>Vine,</hi> a <hi>Line,</hi> a <hi>Brute,</hi> a <hi>Centre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What need is there to diſguiſe words borrowed from other</hi> Languages?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is neceſſary to diſguiſe Words bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from other <hi>Languages,</hi> becauſe no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65531:17"/>free People ſhould have a Foreign Face on their current Words, more than on their current Goin, both being Badges of <hi>Conqueſt</hi> or <hi>Slavery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->† Thus the <hi>Romans</hi> borrowed a multitude of Words from the <hi>Greeks,</hi> which they made their own by altering the <hi>Accent,</hi> curtailing and cutting off their Terminations, with other various Changes.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> e Servile <hi>diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Servile</hi> is diſtinguiſhed into e <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive,</hi> e <hi>Liquid,</hi> and e <hi>Mute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is</hi> e Subjunctive <hi>written?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Subjunctive</hi> is written at the end of a word, after a ſingle <hi>Conſonant,</hi> to make the ſingle <hi>Vowel</hi> before it long.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How can</hi> e Subjunctive, <hi>after a ſingle</hi> Conſonant, <hi>make the ſingle</hi> Vowel <hi>before it long?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Subjunctive</hi> is really ſounded with the ſingle <hi>Vowel</hi> before the <hi>Conſonant,</hi> and ſo makes the <hi>Subjunctive</hi> or latter <hi>Vowel</hi> of a <hi>Diphthong;</hi> otherwiſe it could not make the <hi>Syllable</hi> long, as in the words, <hi>Fire, more, pale,</hi> read, <hi>Fier, moer, pael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is</hi> e Liquid <hi>written?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Liquid</hi> is written at the end of a word, after a <hi>Mute,</hi> and a <hi>Liquid,</hi> but ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſwiftly between them, as in the words,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65531:17"/>
                  <hi>Candle, Troulbe, Apple, Acre,</hi> read rapidly, <hi>Candel, Troubel, Appel, Aker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Has not</hi> e Liquid <hi>ſometimes the force of</hi> e Subjunctive <hi>alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Liquid</hi> has alſo the force of <hi>e Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive,</hi> when the ſingle <hi>Vowel</hi> before the <hi>Mute</hi> and the <hi>Liquid</hi> muſt be ſounded long, as in the words, <hi>Bible, Bridle, Title;</hi> but if it muſt be ſounded ſhort, the <hi>Mute</hi> muſt be doubled, as in <hi>Saddle, Tittle, Juggle,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is</hi> e Mute <hi>written?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Mute</hi> is written at the end of a word, after <hi>c</hi> and <hi>g,</hi> to ſhew they muſt be ſounded ſoft, as in the words, <hi>chance, change,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> When <hi>g</hi> follows <hi>d</hi> in the ſame Syllable, it needs not <hi>e Mute</hi> after it, to make it ſoft, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot then be pronounced hard, as in <hi>Judg, Judgment.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is</hi> e Mute <hi>written any where elſe, but after</hi> c <hi>and</hi> g <hi>ſoft?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is no Neceſſity of writing <hi>e Mute</hi> any where but after <hi>c</hi> and <hi>g</hi> ſoft; yet it is often tack'd to many other words, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other Reaſon, than corrupt Cuſtom.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not</hi> e Servile <hi>ſometimes ſuppreſs'd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> E <hi>Servile</hi> is always ſuppreſs'd before an <hi>additional Termination</hi> that begins with a <hi>Vowel,</hi> to avoid the concurrence of two <hi>Vowels,</hi> which might ſeem to make a <hi>Diph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thong;</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65531:18"/>as, <hi>Time, timing,</hi> not <hi>timeing; Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, troubled,</hi> not <hi>troubleed; change, changed,</hi> not <hi>changeed;</hi> but <hi>e Mute</hi> muſt not be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd before the <hi>Vowel a,</hi> leſt <hi>c</hi> or <hi>g</hi> ſoft ſhould be ſounded hard; as in the words, <hi>ferviceable, changeable,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which are the additional Terminations that begin with a</hi> Vowel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The additional Terminations that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with a <hi>Vowel,</hi> are <hi>ed, ing, en, er, es, eſt, eth, iſh, able, age, ance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if an-additional Termination that begins with a</hi> Vowel, <hi>come after a ſingle</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant, <hi>with a ſhort</hi> Vowel <hi>before it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If an addi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ional Termination that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins with a <hi>Vorel,</hi> come after a ſingle <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant</hi> with a ſhort <hi>Vowel</hi> before it, then the ſingle <hi>Conſonant</hi> muſt be doubled, leſt <hi>e Subjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> ſhould ſeem to be ſuppreſs'd; as, <hi>run, runneth; tun, tunned; writ, written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> When <hi>c</hi> hard is doubled before an-addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Termination, we write it by <hi>ck</hi> as <hi>bac, backing:</hi> When <hi>g</hi> hard is doubled before an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ional Termination, both are ſounded hard, as, <hi>beg, begging.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the</hi> Vowel e <hi>ſounded at the end of any</hi> Engliſh <hi>word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Vowel e</hi> is not both written and ſounded at the end of any <hi>Engliſh</hi> word, except <hi>the;</hi> in all other <hi>Engliſh</hi> words, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65531:18"/>end in the ſound of <hi>e,</hi> we write the <hi>Diph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thong ea</hi> inſtead of <hi>e;</hi> as in <hi>yea, plea, Sea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a word rightly divided into</hi> Syllables?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A word is rightly divided into <hi>Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> by this one Rule, <hi>viz.</hi> Stop at every ſingle or double <hi>Vowel;</hi> and if one or more <hi>Conſonants</hi> follow, join them with the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Vowel,</hi> as in the words, <hi>Cre-a-tor, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Ma-ſter;</hi> but if any of them cannot be joyned together in the ſame <hi>Syllable</hi> with the following <hi>Vowel,</hi> it muſt of neceſſity be joyned with the foregoing <hi>Vowel,</hi> as in the words, <hi>Mul-ti-tude, Mat-ter, Ser-pent;</hi> where you may obſerve, that <hi>lt, tt, rp,</hi> are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated becauſe they cannot be ſounded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the following <hi>Vowel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Conſonants <hi>can be joyned together in the ſame</hi> Syllable <hi>with the following</hi> Vowel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Mute,</hi> and <hi>a Liquid</hi> after it, can always be joyned together in the ſame <hi>Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> with the following <hi>Vowel;</hi> as likewiſe <hi>s</hi> with ſeveral other <hi>Conſonants,</hi> which may be known by ſounding them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are compound words divided in</hi> Spelling?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In compound words the compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts are always ſeparated in <hi>Spelling,</hi> as in the words, <hi>mis-take, un-eaſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To which</hi> Vowel <hi>muſt</hi> x <hi>be joyned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. X</hi> is not properly one ſingle Letter, but an abbreviature of <hi>c s,</hi> which cannot,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65531:19"/>without force, be ſounded with the <hi>Vowel</hi> after it; and therefore muſt of neceſſity be ſounded with the <hi>Vowel</hi> before it, as in the word, <hi>Com-plex-i-on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if a word muſt be divided at the end of a Line?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If for want of room, a word muſt be divided at the end of a Line, a <hi>Syllable</hi> muſt not be broken, but a <hi>Hyphen</hi> or Mark of Union made at the end of the line, thus—</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are words called in reſpect of their</hi> Syllables?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A word of one <hi>Syllable</hi> is called a <hi>Monoſyllable,</hi> a word of two a <hi>Diſſyllable;</hi> any word of more than two a <hi>Polyſyllable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are</hi> Syllables <hi>diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of Quantity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Syllables</hi> in reſpect of the quantity, or ſpace of time in which they are pronounced, are diſtinguiſhed into <hi>long</hi> and <hi>ſhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Syllables <hi>are</hi> long?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All <hi>Diphthongs</hi> are naturally <hi>long,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe two <hi>Vowels</hi> pronounced together in one continued Breath, take up more time than one ſingle <hi>Vowel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Syllables <hi>are</hi> ſhort?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All ſingle <hi>Vowels</hi> are naturally <hi>ſhort,</hi> except they be made <hi>long</hi> by the <hi>Accent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:65531:19"/>
               <head>Of the Accent.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the</hi> Accent?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Accent</hi> or <hi>Tone,</hi> is the extenſion of the Voice, in pronouncing one <hi>Syllable</hi> in a word <hi>louder</hi> and <hi>longer</hi> than the reſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are</hi> Syllables <hi>diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of the</hi> Accent?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Syllables,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Accent,</hi> are diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Acute</hi> and <hi>Grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an</hi> Acute Syllable?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>Acute Syllable</hi> is that which muſt be ſounded <hi>ſharp</hi> and <hi>long.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Grave Syllable?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Grave Syllable</hi> is that which muſt be ſounded <hi>flat,</hi> and <hi>ſhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many</hi> Syllables <hi>in a word are to be ſounded</hi> Acute?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In every word of more than one <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable,</hi> whether it be ſimple or compound, there is but one <hi>Syllable</hi> ſounded <hi>acute,</hi> all the reſt are ſounded <hi>grave,</hi> whether they be ſingle <hi>Vowels</hi> or <hi>Diphthongs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>How ſhall one know which</hi> Syllable <hi>in a word is to be ſounded</hi> acute?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>acute Syllable</hi> is known by the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of every <hi>Language;</hi> for tho Nature has put one <hi>acute</hi> ſound in every word of more than one <hi>Syllable,</hi> yet it is the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of every <hi>Nation</hi> that determins it to this or that <hi>Syllable.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65531:20"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a ſingle</hi> Vowel <hi>made</hi> long <hi>by the accent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In every <hi>acute Syllable</hi> there is a <hi>Diph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thong,</hi> or <hi>double ſound;</hi> for if the <hi>Vowel</hi> be ſingle, it is ſounded double in one continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Breath; and ſometimes written double.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there no Mark to know the</hi> acute Syllable?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Greeks</hi> put this Mark over the <hi>acute Vowel</hi> or <hi>Diphthong;</hi> which, if done in other <hi>Languages,</hi> their Pronounciation would not be ſo difficult for <hi>Foreigners</hi> to learn, as uſually it is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are there not ſome words diſtinguiſhed only by the</hi> Accent?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are many words written alike, and only diſtinguiſhed by the <hi>accent;</hi> as for Example, <hi>òbject</hi> is a Noun, but <hi>objèct</hi> is a Verb; <hi>orátor</hi> is <hi>Latin,</hi> but <hi>òrator</hi> is <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the principal thing in learning any</hi> Language?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt and principal thing in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any <hi>Language,</hi> is to get the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounciation of the words; for he that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents a word contrary to the Cuſtom of the <hi>Language,</hi> ſpeaks barbarouſly, and makes himſelf ridiculous to the Hearers; as if one ſhould in Engliſh ſay, <hi>Rélation</hi> for <hi>Relátion; Orátor</hi> for <hi>órator; facúlty</hi> for <hi>fáculty; Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſáry</hi> for <hi>ádverſary; Audítor</hi> for <hi>áuditor,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are there not three</hi> Accents?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is no more than one <hi>Accent,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65531:20"/>but the ancient Grammarians, finding three ſeveral marks for the <hi>Acute</hi> Syllable in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue, imagined there were three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Accents;</hi> which is not only falſe, but ſimply impoſſible in the Nature of Speech. That which they call the <hi>Grave Accent</hi> is always a mark of the <hi>Acute</hi> Syllable, and is nothing elſe but the <hi>Acute</hi> mark turned backward, when the <hi>Accent</hi> is on the laſt Syllable of a Word, leaſt it ſhould run forward into the following Word, and cauſe Confuſion in Reading; for <hi>Grave</hi> Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables never had any mark becauſe they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver needed any, all the Syllabes in a Word except one, being <hi>Grave,</hi> whether they be Single <hi>Vowels</hi> or <hi>Diphthongs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which they call the <hi>Circumſlex-Accent,</hi> is always a mark of the <hi>acute</hi> Syllable, and is chiefly uſed when two Syllables are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into one.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many Syllables can come under one</hi> Accent?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There can come eight or nine Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyables under one <hi>accent,</hi> and any more is a force upon Nature; but thoſe Words are moſt Harmonious that do not exceed ſix or ſeven Syllables.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->† The <hi>Engliſh</hi> for the moſt part love to <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> Syllable of a Word, which is more Vehement and <hi>Maſculine.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> for the moſt part love to <hi>Accent</hi> the laſt Syllable of a Word, which is too Soft and <hi>Feminine.</hi> The <hi>Latins</hi> do almoſt always <hi>Accent</hi> the penult, or antepenult Syllable of a Word, which makes the beſt and moſt agreeable Harmony in <hi>Speech,</hi> and in that regard the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue excels all other <hi>Languages.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The <hi>penult</hi> is the laſt Syllable of a Word but one, the <hi>Antepenult</hi> is the Syllable before the <hi>Penult,</hi> or the <hi>third</hi> Syllable from the end of the Word.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65531:21"/>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Words.</head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is a</hi> Word?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A <hi>Word</hi> is an <hi>Articulate ſound</hi> that ſignifies ſomething by the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of any <hi>Language.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an</hi> Articulate <hi>Sound?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>Articulate</hi> Sound is that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Syllables,</hi> as it were of Joints.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Words diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of</hi> Derivation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Words in reſpect of <hi>Derivation</hi> are diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>Derivative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Primitive <hi>Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Primitive</hi> Word is that which is not derived of another, as <hi>good, man, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>What is a</hi> Derivative <hi>Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65531:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Derivative</hi> Word, is that which is derived of another, as <hi>Goodneſs, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Words diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of</hi> Compoſition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Words in reſpect of <hi>Compoſition</hi> are diſtinguiſht into <hi>Simple</hi> and <hi>Compound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Simple <hi>Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Simple</hi> Word is that which is not Compounded of two Words, as a <hi>Book,</hi> a <hi>School,</hi> a <hi>Stone,</hi> a <hi>Houſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Compound <hi>Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Compound</hi> Word, is that which is Compounded of two or more Words; as a <hi>Book-ſeller,</hi> Compounded of Book and Seller; a <hi>VVatch-man,</hi> of Watch and Man.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are there not</hi> Half Compounds?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we Compound two or more Words, without putting them under one <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> we only join them with a <hi>Hyphen</hi> or mark of Union, and ſuch may be called <hi>Half-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds,</hi> as a <hi>Water-Spider.</hi> But if the Cuſtom of the Language has put them under one <hi>Accent,</hi> we muſt write them in one Word without a <hi>Hyphen,</hi> as a <hi>Shoomaker,</hi> not a <hi>Shoó-maker;</hi> a <hi>Highlander,</hi> not a <hi>High-lander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many Kinds of Words are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are four kinds of Words, a <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> an <hi>Adjective,</hi> a <hi>Verb,</hi> and a <hi>Particle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How do you know there are but four kinds of Words?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:65531:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I know there are but four kinds of Words, becauſe there are but four kinds of things to be ſignified by Words: for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is in the whole <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> is either a <hi>thing,</hi> or the <hi>manner</hi> of a thing; the <hi>action</hi> of a thing, or the <hi>manner</hi> of an Action.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are theſe four kinds of</hi> Things <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Things</hi> themſelves are ſignified by <hi>Subſtantives;</hi> the manners of things, by <hi>Adjectives;</hi> the Actions of things, by Verbs; the manners of Actions, by <hi>Particles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a</hi> Subſtantive.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Subſtantive</hi> is a Word that ſignifies a thing whether <hi>Corporeal</hi> or <hi>Incorporeal;</hi> as <hi>God, Man, Reaſon, VViſdom, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a</hi> Corporeal <hi>thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Corporeal</hi> or Bodily thing is that which can be perceived by the <hi>Senſes, and may be ſeen or felt;</hi> as, a <hi>Boy,</hi> a <hi>Book,</hi> a <hi>Pen,</hi> a <hi>School,</hi> a <hi>Table, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is an</hi> Incorporeal <hi>thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>Incorporeal</hi> thing is that which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perceived by the <hi>Senſes</hi> but only by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and cannot be ſeen nor felt, as <hi>Juſtice, Knowledg, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Goodneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>be known?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every Word that can be declined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in good Senſe, in any ones Native Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, is a <hi>Subſtantive;</hi> as for Example, I I know the Word, <hi>Man,</hi> is a <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> becauſe I can decline it in good Senſe, thus,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65531:22"/>
                  <hi>of Man, to Man, with Man:</hi> No other kind of Word ſo Declined can make Senſe, for if I ſay, <hi>of againſt, to againſt, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt,</hi> it is Nonſenſe, by which I know againſt is not a <hi>Subſtantive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> A <hi>Subſtantive</hi> is alſo called a <hi>Noun,</hi> or a <hi>Noun-ſubſtantive,</hi> or a <hi>Name.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of</hi> Subſtantives <hi>are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are two ſorts of <hi>Subſtantives, Common</hi> and <hi>Proper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is</hi> a Common or <hi>Appellative Noun?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Common or <hi>Appellative Noun,</hi> is a Word that ſignifies one kind of thing, and is Common to all of that kind, as the Words, <hi>Man, City, Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a Proper Name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Proper Name is a Word given to any individual thing of a kind, by which it is known and diſtinguiſhed from others of the ſame kind, as <hi>Peter, London, England.</hi> Man is one kind of thing, <hi>Peter</hi> is one of that kind, <hi>John</hi> another, <hi>James</hi> another. A City is one kind of thing, <hi>London</hi> is one of that kind, <hi>Paris</hi> another, <hi>Rome</hi> another. A. Kingdom is one kind of thing, <hi>England</hi> is one of that kind, <hi>France</hi> another, <hi>Italy</hi> another.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Have not Perſons two Proper Names?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:65531:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> At firſt one Perſon had but one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Name, as <hi>Adam, Abraham, Jacob,</hi> but afterward when Mankind multiplied, the ſame Proper Name was given to ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which made it neceſſary formore par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſtinction to add a Second: the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of which is uſually called the <hi>Name,</hi> the latter <hi>Sirname,</hi> as <hi>Charles Stuart;</hi> ſome Perſons have three or more proper Names, as <hi>Julius Caeſar Scaliger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not Common Nouns ſometimes made Proper Names?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Common Nouns</hi> are ſometimes made <hi>Proper Names,</hi> but then regard is had only to the Sound, not to the Signification; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe theſe <hi>Sirnames, King, Knight, Thom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and ſuch like, could not in good Senſe be given to the Females of the Families ſo called.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can Proper Names be Tranſlated from one Language to another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Proper Names as ſuch cannot be Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated from one Language to another, for if the Sound be changed the proper Name is loſt. As for Example we muſt not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate the <hi>Latin</hi> Proper Name, <hi>Piſcator, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher,</hi> nor the <hi>Engliſh</hi> proper Name, <hi>Fiſher, Piſcator:</hi> Yet the <hi>Latins</hi> to Accommodate Forein proper Names to their own <hi>Idiom,</hi> do often add to them a <hi>Latin</hi> Termination, as, <hi>us a, um,</hi> thus they call <hi>Jacob, Jacobus, Fiſher, Fiſherus,</hi> and Forreiners for the ſame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65531:23"/>Reaſon cut off the <hi>Latin</hi> Terminations, thus we call <hi>Paulus, Paul; Marcus, Mark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is it neceſſary to give a proper Name to every Individual thing of a kind?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If there be but one Individual thing of a kind, it is not neceſſary to give it a proper Name, ſince there is no other of the kind, from which it needs to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, as <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Sun, &amp;c.</hi> And where there are more of the ſame kind, none of them needs a Proper Name, but Men and ſuch things as Men have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent occaſion to mention in particular, as <hi>Countries, Iſlands, Towns, Villages, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Mountains, Ships,</hi> and many other individual things of other kinds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>S</hi> Servile.</head>
               <p>Q. Why is <hi>s</hi> Servile ſo called?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> S Servile is ſo called, becauſe it ſerves for ſeveral uſes, in the Variation of <hi>Nouns</hi> and <hi>Verbs</hi> in Engliſh.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is s Servile diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> S Servile is diſtinguiſhed into <hi>s</hi> Plural, <hi>s</hi> Poſſeſſive, and <hi>s</hi> Perſonal.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is</hi> s <hi>Plural writen?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. S</hi> Plural, is writen at the end of a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive</hi> Singular, to make it Plural, as a <hi>Boy, Boys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is</hi> s <hi>Poſſeſſive written?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:65531:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65531:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:65531:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65531:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:65531:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> S Poſſeſſive, is written at the end of a <hi>Subſtantive</hi> Singular or Plural, to make it the Genitive of the Poſſeſſor, as the <hi>Lords houſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is</hi> s <hi>Perſonal written?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. s</hi> Perſonal is added to the Theam of a <hi>Verb,</hi> to make it the third Perſon Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as, <hi>Irun, he runs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Syllable</hi> es <hi>ſometimes uſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of</hi> s <hi>Servile?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Syllable <hi>es</hi> is always uſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>s</hi> Servile, when the Word ends in <hi>s,</hi> or in the Sound of <hi>s,</hi> becauſe <hi>s</hi> alone can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſtinguiſhed in the Sound, as, <hi>Caſe, Caſes, Corps, Corpſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Words end in the Sound of e?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Words that end in <hi>ſh, z, ch, e,</hi> and <hi>g</hi> ſoft have the Sound of <hi>s,</hi> as <hi>Fiſh, Fiſhes, Prize, Prizes, Church, Churches, Race, Races, Age, Ages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note.</hi> When <hi>s</hi> Servile comes after <hi>e</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, <hi>es</hi> doth not increaſe the Number of Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in a Word, becauſe <hi>e</hi> is Sounded before the final Conſonant, and <hi>s</hi> immediatly after it; thus <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> are bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Monoſyllables; <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>Tables,</hi> are both diſſyllables: but when <hi>es</hi> comes after <hi>s</hi> or the ſound of <hi>s</hi> it makes a Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble more in a Word, becauſe <hi>s</hi> alone cannot be diſtinguiſht in the Sound, thus, <hi>Page, Grace, Prize,</hi> are Monoſyllables, but, <hi>Pages, Graces, Prizes,</hi> are Diſſyllables.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note.</hi> When <hi>e</hi> Subjunctive or <hi>e</hi> Mute is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt before a Vowel, then the final Conſonant is joyned in the ſame Syllable with that Vowel, as Time, Ti-ming, not Tim-ing, Age, A-ged, not Ag-ed; when <hi>e</hi> Liquid is ſuppreſt before a Vowel, the Mute and the Liquid are both join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame Syllable with that Vowel, as, Trou-ble, Trou-bler.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65531:26"/>
               <head>Of Number.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are</hi> Subſtantives <hi>diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of Number?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Subſtantives</hi> in reſpect of Number are diſtinguiſhed into Singular and Plural; the Singular Number denotes one, as, <hi>a Houſe;</hi> the Plural Number denotes more than one, as, <hi>Houſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Plural Number made in</hi> Engliſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Plural Number is uſually made in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by adding <hi>s</hi> to the <hi>Subſtantive</hi> Singular, or <hi>es</hi> when the Pronunciation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it; as, a <hi>Book, Books,</hi> a <hi>Pen, Pens,</hi> a <hi>Church, Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Plural Number made other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by</hi> s <hi>or</hi> es?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Some <hi>Nouns</hi> form the Plural Number otherwiſe than by <hi>s</hi> or <hi>es,</hi> as, <hi>Ox, Oxen. Child, Children. Man, Men. VVoman,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65531:27"/>VVomen, Tooth, Teeth, Gooſe, Geeſe, Mouſe, Mice, Louſe, Lice, Foot, Feet,</hi> a <hi>Cow, Kine,</hi> or <hi>Cows;</hi> the Words <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Swine</hi> are both Singular and Plural. In ſome <hi>Nouns f</hi> is turned into <hi>v</hi> a Letter of the ſame Organ for eaſe of Pronounciation, as, <hi>Knife, Knives, VVife, VVives, Life, Lives.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Declining of a <hi>Noun.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Declining of a</hi> Noun?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Declining of a <hi>Noun</hi> is the Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation thereof, according to the various <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Caſe</hi> of the thing ſignified by it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many Caſes are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are ſix Caſes, Viz. <hi>Nominative, Vocative, Genitive, Dative, Ablative,</hi> and <hi>Accuſative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is a</hi> Noun <hi>in the Nominative State or Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Noun</hi> is in the Nominative <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Caſe,</hi> when 'tis the Subject of a <hi>Verb,</hi> and then it uſually comes in good Senſe before the <hi>Verb,</hi> as <hi>the Maſter teaches, the Scholar Learns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhen is a</hi> Noun <hi>in the Vocative Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Noun</hi> is in the Vocative Caſe, when it is the Perſon to whom we ſpeak or call, as, <hi>Maſter, I can ſay. Child, Read your Leſſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>VVhen is a</hi> Noun <hi>in the Genitive Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:65531:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Noun</hi> is in the Genitive Caſe, when it is the Poſſeſſor of ſome other thing poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as, <hi>the Book of the Maſter,</hi> or, <hi>the Maſters Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Genitive formed in</hi> Engliſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In <hi>Engliſh</hi> the Genitive is formed two ways, either by putting the Prepoſition <hi>of</hi> before the <hi>Subſtantive</hi> or <hi>s</hi> after it, (or <hi>es</hi> when the neceſſity of Pronounciation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires;) when <hi>of</hi> is before the Genitive, the poſſeſſed <hi>Subſtantive</hi> comes before <hi>of:</hi> but when <hi>s</hi> or <hi>es</hi> is added to the <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> the poſſeſſed <hi>Subſtantive</hi> comes after it. As the <hi>Maſters Care,</hi> or, the <hi>Care</hi> of the <hi>Maſter.</hi> An <hi>aſſes Milk,</hi> or, the <hi>Milk</hi> of an <hi>aſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not</hi> es <hi>Poſſeſſive ſometimes omitted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Es</hi> Poſſeſſive is often omitted for eaſineſs of Pronunciation, as <hi>Priamus Son,</hi> for <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amuſes Son;</hi> the <hi>Horſes bridles,</hi> for the <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhen is a</hi> Noun <hi>in the Dative Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Noun</hi> is in the Dative Caſe, when it is the thing to which any other thing is applyed by ſome <hi>Verb</hi> or <hi>Adjective.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>How is the Dative known in</hi> Engliſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In <hi>Engliſh</hi> the Dative is uſually known by the Prepoſition <hi>to,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>for</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it, and then the applyed Word comes before the Prepoſition, as for Example, <hi>Strong Drink is hurtful to Children or for Children. I ſaid my Leſſon to the Master.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:65531:28"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is a</hi> Noun <hi>in the Ablative Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Noun</hi> is in the Ablative Caſe, when it comes after any of theſe Prepoſitions, <hi>with, from, in,</hi> or <hi>by, &amp;c. as with my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, from my Father, in the School, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is a</hi> Noun <hi>in the Accuſative Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Noun</hi> is in the Accuſative Caſe, when it is the object of Action, and then it uſually comes after a <hi>Verb</hi> or <hi>Participle</hi> of an active Signification. As for Example, <hi>VVorſhip God, Honour thy Parents, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Caſes are alike in</hi> Engliſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Nominative, Vocative, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſative are alike in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the <hi>Nom.</hi> Sing. <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>Gen.</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Mans,</hi> the <hi>Dat.</hi> to <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>Abl.</hi> from <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>Accuſ. Man, Nom.</hi> Plur. <hi>Men,</hi> the <hi>Gen.</hi> or <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Mens,</hi> the <hi>Dat.</hi> to <hi>Men,</hi> the <hi>Abl.</hi> from <hi>Men,</hi> the <hi>Accuſ Men</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Perſonal</hi> Subſtantive, <hi>I,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Perſonal <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> I, is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly declined, thus, <hi>Nom.</hi> Sing. I, <hi>Gen.</hi> of <hi>me, Dat.</hi> to <hi>me, Abl.</hi> to <hi>me, Accuſ. me, Now.</hi> Plur. <hi>we, Gen.</hi> of <hi>us, Dat.</hi> to <hi>us, Abl.</hi> from <hi>us. Accuſ. us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the</hi> Perſonal Subſtantive, <hi>Thou, declined?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Perſonal Subſtantive, Thou,</hi> is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularly Declined thus, Nom. Sing. <hi>Thou,</hi> Voc. <hi>thou,</hi> Gen. <hi>of thee,</hi> Dat. <hi>to thee,</hi> Abl.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65531:28"/>
                  <hi>from thee,</hi> Accuſ. <hi>thee,</hi> Nom. Plur. <hi>Ye,</hi> or <hi>you,</hi> Voc. <hi>ye,</hi> or <hi>you,</hi> Gen. <hi>of you,</hi> Dat. <hi>to you,</hi> Abl. <hi>from you,</hi> Accuſ. <hi>you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Genders</hi> of <hi>Nouns.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are</hi> Subſtantives <hi>diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of</hi> Gender.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Subſtantives</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Gender</hi> are diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Maſculine, Feminine,</hi> and <hi>Neuter;</hi> the Maſculine Gender is the <hi>he</hi> kind, the Feminine the <hi>ſhe</hi> kind, the Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gender any thing that is neither <hi>he,</hi> nor <hi>ſhe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are the</hi> Genders <hi>ſignified in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Engliſh the Maſculine <hi>Gender</hi> is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by <hi>he,</hi> the Feminine by <hi>ſhe,</hi> the Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by <hi>it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nouns are of the</hi> Maſculine <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All Nouns that are ſaid of the <hi>he</hi> kind only, are of the <hi>Maſculine</hi> Gender, as a <hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>Brother,</hi> a <hi>Son, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Nouns <hi>are of the</hi> Feminine <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All Nouns that are ſaid of the <hi>ſhe</hi> kind only, are of the <hi>Feminine</hi> Gender, as a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> a <hi>Daughter,</hi> a <hi>Siſter, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nouns are of the</hi> Neuter <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:65531:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All Nouns that are not ſaid of the <hi>he</hi> kind only, nor of the <hi>ſhe</hi> kind only, are of the <hi>Neuter Gender,</hi> as a <hi>Creature,</hi> a <hi>Thing,</hi> a <hi>Houſe,</hi> a <hi>Book,</hi> a <hi>Table, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not ſome Nouns ſaid both of the</hi> Males <hi>and</hi> Females <hi>of a kind?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are ſome Nouns ſaid both of the <hi>Males</hi> and <hi>Females</hi> of a kind without diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and they are called <hi>Epicens</hi> or Nouns common to both Sexes, becauſe they ſignify the Species or common Nature of both without regard to either, and therefore they are properly of the <hi>Neuter</hi> Gender: as a <hi>Child,</hi> a <hi>Sparrow,</hi> a <hi>Slave, &amp;c.</hi> But when <hi>Epicens</hi> are particularly applyed to one Sex diſtinct from the other, they alſo admit the Gender of the Sex, to which they are applied: As for Example, I may ſay in good Senſe, <hi>The Nurſe took the</hi> Child, <hi>and gave</hi> it <hi>ſuck,</hi> or (with regard to the Sex) <hi>gave</hi> him <hi>ſuck,</hi> or <hi>gave</hi> her <hi>ſuck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note. <hi>In</hi> Epicens <hi>the Sex is often diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the Words,</hi> Male, Female, he, ſhe, <hi>and ſuch like Sex-diſtinguiſhing Words,</hi> as a Male-Child, a Female-Child, a He-aſs, a She-aſs, a Cock-ſparrow, a Hen ſparrow.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:65531:29"/>
               <head>Of an <hi>Adjective.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an</hi> Adjective?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>Adjective</hi> is a Word, that ſignifies the <hi>Manner</hi> or <hi>Quality</hi> of a thing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know an</hi> Adjective?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every Word that can be declined in good Senſe with a <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> and without a <hi>Subſtantive</hi> does not make Senſe, is an <hi>Adjective,</hi> as the Words, <hi>Wiſe, Fooliſh, White, Black,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How do you know the Word</hi> Wiſe is an Adjective?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I know the Word Wiſe is an <hi>Adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive,</hi> becauſe I can decline it in good Senſe with a <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> thus, <hi>A Wiſe Man, of a Wiſe Man, to a Wiſe Man, with a Wiſe Man:</hi> And without a <hi>Subſtantive</hi> it does not make Senſe, as, <hi>I Love Wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are all</hi> Adjectives <hi>ſaid in the</hi> Vocative <hi>Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Adjectives a</hi> and <hi>the</hi> and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>Adjectives,</hi> are not ſaid in the <hi>Voc.</hi> Caſe, becauſe they always denote the Perſon, or thing <hi>ſpoken of,</hi> but the <hi>Voc.</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways denotes the Perſon or thing <hi>ſpoken to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can</hi> a <hi>or</hi> the <hi>be joined with a proper Name in good Sence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. A</hi> or <hi>the,</hi> Or any other <hi>Adjective,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in good Senſe be joined with a Proper
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65531:30"/>Name, as ſuch; becauſe every <hi>Adjective</hi> qualifies and determines ſome kind of thing, but a Proper Name is no kind of thing, but a meer ſound, by which an individual thing of a kind is diſtinguiſhed from other individuals of the ſame kind. But when a Proper Name is put for a common Noun, or when a common Noun is underſtood with it, then it admits <hi>a</hi> or <hi>the,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adjective</hi> in good Senſe.</p>
               <p>Thus I can ſay in good Senſe, a <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>City,</hi> but not a <hi>John,</hi> the <hi>London;</hi> I can ſay, a <hi>Solomon for a very Wiſe Man, a Judas for a very treacherous Man,</hi> and if I ſay, <hi>Wiſe Solomon,</hi> or <hi>treacherous Judas,</hi> the common <hi>Subſtantive Man</hi> is underſtood.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Do</hi> Adjectives <hi>admit</hi> s <hi>to make them</hi> Plural?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Engliſh the <hi>Adjectives</hi> are alike in both Numbers; but when they are uſed as <hi>Subſtantives,</hi> then they admit <hi>s</hi> to make them <hi>Plural,</hi> as, <hi>ſecrets</hi> for <hi>ſecret things, goods,</hi> for <hi>good things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is the</hi> Adjective a <hi>ſaid in the</hi> Plural <hi>Number?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Adjective a</hi> is not ſaid in the <hi>Plural</hi> Number; becauſe it always denotes one, or ſome one indefinitely, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be ſaid in the Plural Number. We ſay <hi>a</hi> before a <hi>Conſonant,</hi> and <hi>an</hi> before a <hi>Vowel</hi> for eaſineſs of Pronounciation, as a <hi>a man,</hi> not <hi>an man;</hi> an <hi>aſs,</hi> not a <hi>aſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65531:30"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is the Adjective</hi> the <hi>ſaid in the Plural Number?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Adjective <hi>the</hi> denotes one or more things particularly known, or ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be known, and therefore can be ſaid in both Numbers, as <hi>the boy,</hi> or <hi>the boys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Adjective <hi>this</hi> makes <hi>theſe</hi> in the Plural Number; <hi>that</hi> makes <hi>thoſe; ſelf</hi> makes <hi>ſelves.</hi> The Adjective <hi>who</hi> makes <hi>whoſe</hi> or <hi>of whom</hi> in the Genitive Singular, the Dative <hi>to whom,</hi> the Ablative <hi>from whom,</hi> and ſo Plurally.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p>Q. <hi>The Adjectives,</hi> he, ſhe, it, <hi>are thus Declined?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nom. Sing. <hi>He,</hi> Gen. <hi>his,</hi> or <hi>of him,</hi> Dat. <hi>to him,</hi> Abl, <hi>from him.</hi> Nom. Sing. <hi>She,</hi> Gen. <hi>hers,</hi> or <hi>of her,</hi> or <hi>her,</hi> Dat. <hi>to her,</hi> Abl. <hi>from her,</hi> Accuſ. <hi>her.</hi> Nom. Sing. <hi>It,</hi> Gen. <hi>Its,</hi> or <hi>of it,</hi> Dat. <hi>to it,</hi> Abl. <hi>from it,</hi> Accuſ. <hi>it. He, She, It,</hi> have the ſame Plural Number. Nom. Plur. <hi>They,</hi> Gen. <hi>their, theirs,</hi> or <hi>of them,</hi> Dat. <hi>to them,</hi> Abl. <hi>from them,</hi> Accuſ. <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Compariſon.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are</hi> Adjectives <hi>diſtinguiſht in reſpect of</hi> Compariſon?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Adjectives</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Compariſon</hi> are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65531:31"/>diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Compárable</hi> and <hi>incompá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> comparable <hi>Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A <hi>Comparable</hi> or <hi>Poſitive</hi> Adjective is that whoſe Signification can be increaſed, as <hi>hard, ſoft, long, ſhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may one know a</hi> comparable <hi>or</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive <hi>Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Every <hi>Adjective</hi> that in good Senſe admits before it, the Particles <hi>more, moſt,</hi> or <hi>very,</hi> is a <hi>Comparable</hi> or <hi>Poſitive</hi> Adjective; thus I know <hi>hard</hi> is a <hi>Poſitive</hi> Adjective, becauſe I can ſay in good Senſe, <hi>more hard, moſt hard, very hard,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Adjectives <hi>are formed from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive</hi> Adjectives?</p>
               <p>A. From Poſitive Adjectives are formed <hi>Comparative</hi> and <hi>Superlative</hi> Adjectives.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Comparative <hi>Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A <hi>Comparative</hi> Adjective is that which ſignifies the ſame as the Poſitive with the Particle <hi>more</hi> before it; as <hi>harder,</hi> which is the ſame as <hi>more hard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the</hi> comparative <hi>formed in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Comparative</hi> is formed in Engliſh, by adding the Termination <hi>er</hi> to the Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; as <hi>harder, ſofter, longer, ſhorter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Superlative <hi>Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A <hi>Superlative</hi> Adjective is that which ſignifies the ſame as the Poſitive with the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65531:31"/>Particle <hi>moſt</hi> before it; as <hi>hardeſt,</hi> which is the ſame, as <hi>moſt hard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the</hi> Superlative <hi>formed in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Superlative</hi> is formed in Engliſh, by adding the Termination <hi>eſt</hi> to the Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as, <hi>hardeſt, ſofteſt, longeſt, ſhorteſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are there not ſome</hi> Comparative <hi>and</hi> Superlative <hi>Adjctives formed irregularly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The Poſitive Adjectives, <hi>good, bad, little, much,</hi> form their <hi>Comparatives,</hi> and <hi>Superlatives</hi> irregularly; as <hi>Good, better, beſt; bad, worſe, worſt; little, leſs, leaſt; much, more, moſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note. <hi>To</hi> Compare <hi>an</hi> Adjective <hi>in Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, is to give the</hi> Comparative <hi>and</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative <hi>of it, as,</hi> hard, harder, hardeſt. <hi>The Grammarians call them the three degrees of</hi> Compariſon; <hi>as for Example,</hi> hard, <hi>is of the</hi> Poſitive <hi>degree;</hi> harder, <hi>of the</hi> Comparative <hi>degree; and</hi> hardeſt, <hi>of the</hi> Superlative <hi>degree.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an</hi> incomparable <hi>Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. An <hi>Incomparable</hi> Adjective is that, whoſe Signification cannot be encreafed, and admits not before it in good Senſe, the Particles <hi>more, moſt,</hi> or <hi>very;</hi> as <hi>all, ſome, any, &amp;c.</hi> I cannot ſay in good Senſe, <hi>more all, moſt all,</hi> or <hi>very all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:65531:32"/>
               <head>Obſervations on ſome Adjectives.</head>
               <p>Much <hi>makes</hi> many, <hi>in the Plural Number:</hi> Much <hi>with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>of the Plural Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, denotes a great quantity; as,</hi> much wine, <hi>for a great quantity of wine.</hi> Many <hi>with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>of the Plural Number ſignifies a great Number; as,</hi> many men, <hi>for a great Number of Men.</hi> Many a man, <hi>is a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſm, firſt uſed among the Vulgar for many men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More, <hi>with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>of the Singular Number, ſignifies a</hi> greater quantity, <hi>as,</hi> more wine, <hi>or a greater quantity of wine.</hi> More <hi>with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>Plural, ſignifies a a</hi> greater number, <hi>as,</hi> more men, <hi>or a</hi> greater number of men.</p>
               <p>Moſt, <hi>with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>Singular denotes the</hi> greateſt quantity, <hi>as,</hi> moſt of the wine, <hi>or the</hi> greateſt part of the wine. Moſt, <hi>with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>Plural, denotes the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as</hi> moſt men, <hi>or the</hi> greateſt number of men.</p>
               <p>All, <hi>with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>Singular, denotes the</hi> whole quantity, <hi>as,</hi> all the wine, <hi>or the</hi> whole quantity <hi>of the wine.</hi> All <hi>with a a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>Plural, denotes the</hi> whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>as,</hi> all the Children, <hi>for the</hi> whole
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65531:32"/>number <hi>of the Children,</hi> Note. Every <hi>is only ſaid with a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>Singular, as</hi> every man <hi>not</hi> every men. Enough <hi>with a Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Singular denotes a</hi> ſufficient quantity, <hi>as,</hi> enough of wine, <hi>or a</hi> ſufficient quantity of wine. <hi>In the Plural Number, it is</hi> enow, <hi>and denotes a</hi> ſufficient number, <hi>as,</hi> I have Books enow <hi>or a</hi> ſufficient number of Books.</p>
               <p>Who <hi>is uſually ſaid of Perſons,</hi> which <hi>of things, and ſometimes of Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Interrogative</hi> who, <hi>or</hi> which, <hi>asks the Queſtion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n individual things, as,</hi> who is there? <hi>Anſ. Peter. The Interrogative</hi> what, <hi>asks the Queſtion on the</hi> kind, <hi>or</hi> Quality <hi>of things, and alſo on the order of a thing, as,</hi> what is that? <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is a Book. What art thou? <hi>(in the order of number) Anſ. the</hi> firſt, ſecond, third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When the Adjective,</hi> no, <hi>is without a</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive <hi>expreſſed after it, we ſay</hi> none, <hi>as for Example,</hi> Is there no wine? there is none.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Verbs.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Verb?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>A Verb</hi> is a Word that ſignifies the <hi>Action, Paſſion,</hi> or <hi>Being</hi> of a thing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know a</hi> Verb?</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:65531:33"/>
               <p>A. Every word that can be <hi>Conjugated</hi> in good Senſe, with a Subſtantive of the Nominative Caſe before it, and without a Nominative Caſe before it cannot make Senſe, is a Verb. As the Words, <hi>teach, read, run, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How do you know the word</hi> Teach <hi>is a Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. I know the word <hi>teach</hi> is a Verb, becauſe I can Conjugate it in good Senſe, thus, I <hi>teach,</hi> thou <hi>teacheſt,</hi> he <hi>teacheth,</hi> we <hi>teach,</hi> ye <hi>teach,</hi> they <hi>teach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are</hi> Verbs <hi>diſtinguiſhed as to their</hi> Signification?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Verbs</hi> as to their Signification are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed into <hi>Active, Paſſive,</hi> and <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is</hi> a <hi>Verb</hi> Active?</p>
               <p>A. A Verb <hi>Active</hi> is that which denotes the <hi>Action</hi> or doing of its ſubject or Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native Caſe; and admits after it in good Senſe the Accuſative Caſe of its object, or thing it acts upon.</p>
               <p>As for Example, <hi>I call thee, I call him, I call her;</hi> But if I ſay, <hi>I call thou, I call he, I call ſhe,</hi> it is non ſenſe, becauſe theſe are Nominatives, not Accuſatives.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know a Verb</hi> Active?</p>
               <p>A. Every Verb that admits the Auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>do,</hi> or <hi>did,</hi> before it in good Senſe, is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65531:33"/>a Verb <hi>Active,</hi> as, <hi>I ſtand,</hi> or, <hi>I do ſtand; I ſit.</hi> or, <hi>I do ſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Verb</hi> Active <hi>diſtinguiſhed in reſpective of its</hi> Object <hi>or</hi> Accuſative <hi>Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A Verb <hi>Active,</hi> in reſpect of its <hi>Object,</hi> or <hi>Accuſative Caſe,</hi> is diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Tranſitive, and Intranſitive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Verb</hi> Active Tranſitive?</p>
               <p>A. A Verb <hi>Active Tranſitive</hi> is that which admits <hi>Various Objects,</hi> or (which is the ſame) <hi>Various Accuſatives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for Example, I know the Verb <hi>read</hi> is Active Tranſitive, becauſe I can ſay in good Senſe, <hi>I read a Book, I read a Letter, I read the Bible, I read my Leſſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Verb</hi> Active Intranſitive?</p>
               <p>A. A Verb <hi>Active Intranſitive,</hi> is that which in good Senſe admits but of one Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſative, and that of its own Signification. As, <hi>I live a life, I run a race, I go a journey:</hi> But I cannot ſay in good Senſe; <hi>I live a horſe, I run a chamber, I go a houſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Verb</hi> Paſſive?</p>
               <p>A. A <hi>Verb Paſſive</hi> is that which denotes the <hi>Paſſion</hi> or ſuffering of its <hi>Subject</hi> or Nominative Caſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Verb</hi> Paſſive <hi>formed in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. In Engliſh the Verb <hi>Paſſive</hi> is always formed by the Verb <hi>am,</hi> and the <hi>praeter Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiple;</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:65531:34"/>and if either of theſe be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is not Paſſive: as, <hi>I am called, thou art beaten,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Verb</hi> Neuter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Verb <hi>Neuter</hi> is that which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Active nor Paſſive, as the Verbs, <hi>am, may, muſt, can,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Conjugation of Verbs.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the</hi> Conjugation <hi>of a Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Conjugation</hi> of a Verb is the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation</hi> thereof, according to its various <hi>Nominatives,</hi> and various differences of <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Tenſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of</hi> Nominatives <hi>are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are three ſorts of <hi>Nominatives,</hi> called in Grammar <hi>Three Perſons,</hi> Singular, and Plural.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nominatives are of the firſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Singular?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the firſt Perſon Singular, is only one Nominative Singular, <hi>I.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nominatives are of the ſecond perſon Singular?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the ſecond perſon Singular, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one Nominative Singular, <hi>Thou.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nominatives are of the third Perſon Singular?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65531:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. He,</hi> and every other Nominative Singular, is of the third Perſon Singular, except <hi>I</hi> and <hi>Thou.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nominatives are of the firſt Perſon Plural?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the firſt Perſon Plural, is only one Nominative Plural, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nominatives are of the ſecond Perſon Plural?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the ſecond Perſon Plural, is only one Nominative Plural, <hi>ye or you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Nominatives are of the third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Plural?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. They,</hi> and every other Nominative Plural, is of the third Perſon Plural, except <hi>we,</hi> and <hi>ye or you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the Perſons of Verbs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Perſons</hi> of Verbs are their vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Terminations,</hi> accommodated to the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatives of the ſeveral Perſons.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How do the Perſons of Verbs end in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Engliſh Verbs, the firſt Perſon Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, the firſt, ſecond, and third Plural are alike; the ſecond Perſon Singular uſually ends in <hi>eſt;</hi> the third Perſon Singular uſually ends in <hi>eth,</hi> or <hi>s,</hi> or in <hi>es,</hi> when the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Pronounciation requires it: As for Example, <hi>I teach, we teach, ye teach, they teach, thou teacheſt, he teacheth, or teaches.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:65531:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65531:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:65531:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65531:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:65531:37"/>
               <head>Of the Moods.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Verb diſtinguiſhed in reſpect of its</hi> Mood <hi>or manner of expreſſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Verb in reſpect of its <hi>Mood</hi> or manner of expreſſion, is diſtinguiſhed into the <hi>Indicative, Subjunctive,</hi> and <hi>Imperative</hi> Mood.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is a Verb of the</hi> Indicative Mood?</p>
               <p>A. A Verb is of the <hi>Indicative Mood,</hi> when it ſimply <hi>affirms</hi> or <hi>denyes,</hi> or <hi>asks a queſtion.</hi> The Verb alone affirms, as, <hi>I call,</hi> or, <hi>I do call;</hi> it denyes with the Negative Adverb <hi>not</hi> after it, or after its Auxiliary, as, I call <hi>not.</hi> or, I do <hi>not</hi> call: when a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is asked, the Nominat ye comes after the Verb or af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er its Auxiliary, as, <hi>calleſt thou?</hi> or <hi>doſt thou call?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>When is a Verb of the Subjunctive Mood?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Verb is of the Subjunctive Mood, when it is joined to another Verb, by the final Conjunction, <hi>that,</hi> as, <hi>I read</hi> that <hi>I may learn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is a Verb of the</hi> Imperative <hi>Mood?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A Verb is of the <hi>Imperative Mood,</hi> when it <hi>commands</hi> or <hi>prays,</hi> and then the Nominative comes after the Verb, or its Auxiliary, as, <hi>call thou,</hi> or, <hi>do thou call?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65531:37"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Does not the</hi> Imperative <hi>want the firſt Perſon Singular and Plural?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Imperative</hi> wants the firſt Perſon Singular and Plural, becauſe none can <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> or <hi>intreat</hi> themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>Tenſe</hi> or <hi>Time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many</hi> Tenſes <hi>are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. There are five <hi>Tenſes,</hi> the <hi>Preſent,</hi> the <hi>Preter imperfect,</hi> the <hi>Preter perfect,</hi> the <hi>Preter pluperfect,</hi> and the <hi>Future.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the</hi> Preſent Tenſe?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Preſent Tenſe</hi> is the time, that <hi>now is paſſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the</hi> Preter imperfect Tenſe?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Preter imperfect Tenſe</hi> is the Time, that <hi>was then paſſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the</hi> Preter perfect Tenſe?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Preter perfect Tenſe</hi> is the Time, <hi>perfectly paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the</hi> Preter pluperfect Tenſe?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Preter pluperfect Tenſe</hi> is the Time, <hi>more than perfectly paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the</hi> Future Tenſe?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Future Tenſe</hi> is the Time <hi>to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are the</hi> Tenſes <hi>known in</hi> Engliſh?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Tenſes</hi> are known in <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>Auxiliary</hi> Verbs, commonly called the <hi>Signs</hi> of the <hi>Tenſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:65531:38"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>of the</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Tenſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> of the <hi>Preſent Tenſe,</hi> are, <hi>do, doſt, doth, does; am, art, is, are;</hi> as, <hi>I do call, thou doſt call, he doth call, we do call, ye do call, they do call; I am calling, thou art calling,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>of the</hi> Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Tenſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> of the <hi>Imperfect Tenſe,</hi> are, <hi>was, waſt, wert, were;</hi> as, <hi>I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, thou waſt calling, he was calling, we were calling, ye were calling, they were calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>of the</hi> Perfect Tenſe?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> of the <hi>Perfect Tenſe,</hi> are, <hi>have, haſt, has, hath;</hi> as. <hi>I have called, thou haſt called, he has called, we have called, ye have called, they have called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>of the</hi> Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> of the Pluperfect <hi>Tenſe,</hi> are, <hi>had, hadſt;</hi> as, <hi>I had called, thou hadſt called, be had called, we had called, ye had called, they had called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>What are the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>of the</hi> Future Tenſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Auxiliaries of the</hi> Future Tenſe, are, <hi>ſhall, ſhalt; will, wilt;</hi> as, <hi>I ſhall call, thou ſhall call, he ſhall call, we ſhall call, ye ſhall call, they ſhall call; I will call, thou wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t call, he will call,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:65531:38"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>of the</hi> Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>when a Verb has the final Conjunction,</hi> that, <hi>before it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When a Verb has the final Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>that,</hi> before it; the <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> of the preſent <hi>Tenſe,</hi> are, <hi>may, mayſt;</hi> of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, <hi>might, mighteſt;</hi> of the Perfect, <hi>might have;</hi> of the Pluperfect, <hi>might had;</hi> of the Future, <hi>may have;</hi> as for Example, <hi>that I may call, that I might call, that I might have called, that I might had called, that I may have called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>of the</hi> Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> of the <hi>Imperative,</hi> are, <hi>do,</hi> or <hi>be;</hi> as <hi>do thou call, be thou called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not the</hi> Auxiliaries <hi>ſometimes abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Verbs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> have not another Verb or Participle after them, they are not then <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> but abſolute Verbs; and all the <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> are alſo abſolute Verbs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>ſhall, ſhalt;</hi> when <hi>may,</hi> or <hi>might,</hi> has not the final Conjunction, <hi>that,</hi> before it, it is not an <hi>Auxiliary</hi> but an abſolute Verb.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the difference between the</hi> Aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliaries, <hi>ſhall,</hi> and <hi>will?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Shall,</hi> in the firſt Perſons <hi>barely fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells,</hi> in the ſecond and third Perſons it <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> or <hi>threatens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVill</hi> in the firſt Perſons <hi>promiſes</hi> or <hi>threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens,</hi> in the ſecond and third perſons it <hi>barely foretells.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:65531:39"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can any</hi> Tenſe <hi>be expreſs'd without an</hi> Auxiliary?</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Preſent Tenſe,</hi> the <hi>Preter tenſe,</hi> and the <hi>Imperative</hi> can be expreſs'd without an <hi>Auxiliary,</hi> as in the <hi>Preſent Tenſe, I ſee, thou ſeeſt, he ſeeth or ſees, we ſee, ye ſee, they ſee;</hi> in the Preter tenſe, <hi>I ſaw, thou ſaweſt, be ſaw, we ſaw, ye ſaw, they ſaw;</hi> In the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative, ſee thou, ſee he, ſee ye, ſee they.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Imperative ſometimes expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by</hi> let?</p>
               <p>A. In Engliſh we uſually expreſs the third Perſon Singular and Plural of the Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by the Verb Active, <hi>let;</hi> as, <hi>let him call,</hi> for <hi>call he; let them call,</hi> for <hi>call they;</hi> except in ſome forms of Publick Authority, as, <hi>Know all men, Be it enacted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Preter tenſe</hi> of a Verb.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Preter tenſe</hi> or Time paſt of a Verb in Engliſh, is ſometimes of the <hi>Imperfect tenſe,</hi> and ſometimes of the <hi>Perfect tenſe,</hi> and therefore it may be ſimply called the <hi>Preter tenſe,</hi> or the <hi>Preter indefinite,</hi> becauſe it is uncertain, whether it denotes the time im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly paſt, or the time perfectly paſt till the Sence of the Sentence determines it. as, <hi>went, called, paid,</hi> &amp;c. In this Sentence, <hi>I went to School, and ſaid my Leſſon,</hi> the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tenſe went</hi> is of the time perfectly paſt,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65531:39"/>and may be reſolved thus, <hi>after I went to School,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In this Sentence, as, <hi>I went to School, I met my Father,</hi> the <hi>Preter tenſe went</hi> is of the time imperfectly paſt, and may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved thus, <hi>when I was going to School.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note.</hi> The Auxiliary <hi>did,</hi> or <hi>didſt,</hi> is a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indefinite, and may be either of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect or Perfect tenſe. The Particle <hi>whilſt</hi> before the Preter indefinite, always denotes the Imperfect tenſe, as, <hi>whilſt I did write,</hi> or <hi>whilſt I was writing.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>The Particle <hi>after,</hi> or, <hi>after that,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Preter indefinite always denotes the Perfect tenſe and is the ſame as the Auxiliary <hi>having,</hi> as, <hi>after I writ,</hi> or <hi>hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing written.</hi> The Particle <hi>when</hi> is ambiguous; and ſometimes ſignifies <hi>whilſt,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>after,</hi> or <hi>after that.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note.</hi> The Auxiliary <hi>have</hi> with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter participle immediately after it is always Active; but if <hi>been</hi> come between, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Paſſive; thus, <hi>I have called</hi> is Active, but, <hi>I have been called</hi> is Paſſive. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the preſent Particip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is, it is always Active, as, <hi>I have been calling.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:65531:40"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the</hi> Preter tenſe <hi>formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Preter tenſe is regularly form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by adding the Termination <hi>ed</hi> to the Theam, or preſent Tenſe, as, <hi>I call, I call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and ſometimes <hi>e</hi> is omitted for brevity or eaſineſs of Pronounciation, and then the <hi>d</hi> is often changed into <hi>t</hi> a Letter of the ſame Organ, as <hi>diſtinguiſh'd,</hi> for <hi>diſtinguiſhed;</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſht<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> for <hi>diſtinguiſh'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Pretertenſe ſometimes irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Preter tenſe is often irregularly formed, as, from <hi>ſee, ſaw;</hi> from <hi>run, ran;</hi> from <hi>break, broke;</hi> with many more, which uſe will teach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Participles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a</hi> Participle?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Participle is a Verbal Subſtantive, or Adjective, which admits after it ſuch caſe as the Verb of which it is derived.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Subſtantive Participles <hi>are there in Engliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Engliſh there are two Subſtantive Participles, the <hi>Preſent,</hi> and <hi>Perfect infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the</hi> Preſent Infinitive <hi>formed in Engliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Engliſh the Preſent Infinitive is uſually formed, by putting the Prepoſition, <hi>to,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:65531:40"/>before the Theam or Preſent Tenſe of the Verb; as, <hi>to call, to read, to teach,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the</hi> Perfect Infinitive <hi>formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Perfect Infinitive</hi> is uſually form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by putting <hi>to have,</hi> before the Perfect-Tenſe of the Verb; as, <hi>to have called, to have taught;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What</hi> Adjective Participles <hi>are there in Engliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are two <hi>Adjective Participles</hi> in Engliſh, the <hi>Preſent</hi> and <hi>Preter</hi> Participle.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>How is the</hi> Preſent Participle <hi>formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Preſent Participle</hi> is formed by adding the Termination <hi>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> to the Theam or Preſent Tenſe of the Verb, as, <hi>calling, reading, teaching,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ends the Preter Participle in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Engliſh the Preter Participle uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ends in <hi>d, t,</hi> or <hi>n,</hi> as, <hi>called, taught, beaten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>What if the Verb of the Preter Tenſe end in</hi> d <hi>or</hi> t?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A,</hi> If the Verb of the Preter Tenſe end in <hi>d</hi> or <hi>t,</hi> the Preter Participle is the ſame with it, and is only diſtinguiſhed by the Senſe. But if the Verb of the Preter Tenſe, end otherwiſe than in <hi>d</hi> or <hi>t,</hi> then the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Participle uſually ends in <hi>en,</hi> as, <hi>broken,</hi> and oftentimes <hi>e</hi> is left out, as <hi>known,</hi> for <hi>knowen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know the Preter Participle?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:65531:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Word that follows the Auxiliary <hi>have,</hi> in good Senſe, is always the <hi>Preter Participle;</hi> as for Example, I know <hi>ſeen</hi> is the <hi>Preter Participle,</hi> becauſe I can ſay in good Senſe, <hi>I have ſeen,</hi> but I cannot ſay in good Senſe, <hi>I have ſaw;</hi> whence I know that <hi>ſaw</hi> is only a Verb of the Preter Tenſe, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo the Preter Participle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Subſtantive or Copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Verb <hi>am.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q <hi>Why is the Verb Neuter</hi> am, <hi>called a</hi> Subſtantive <hi>or</hi> Copulative <hi>Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Verb Neuter, <hi>am,</hi> is called a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive</hi> or <hi>Copulative</hi> Verb, becauſe it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways couples the Subſtantive of the <hi>Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> after it, to the Subſtantive of the <hi>Subject</hi> before it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not all the Tenſes of a Verb be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by the Verb</hi> am, <hi>and the Participles of the Preſent,</hi> or <hi>Preter Tenſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the Tenſes of a Verb Active, may be expreſt by the Verb <hi>am,</hi> and the preſent Participle, as, <hi>I am calling, I was calling, I have been calling, I had been calling, I ſhall be calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the Tenſes of a Verb Paſſive, may be expreſs'd by the Verb <hi>am,</hi> and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65531:41"/>Participle, and in Engliſh they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo expreſs'd; as, <hi>I am called, I was called, I have been called, I had been called, I ſhall be called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Verb</hi> am <hi>Conjugated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Verb <hi>am</hi> is irregularly Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated thus,</p>
               <p>Preſent Indicative, <hi>I am, thou art, he is, we are, ye are, they are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Imperfect Indicative, <hi>I was, thou waſt, he was, we were, ye were, they were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perfect Indicative, <hi>I have been, thou haſt been, he hath been, we have been, ye have been, they have been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pluperfect Indicative, <hi>I had been, thou hadſt been, he had been, we had been, ye had been, they had been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Future Indicative, <hi>I ſhall be, thou ſhalt be, he ſhall be,</hi> or, <hi>I will be, thou wilt be,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Preſent Sujunctive, that <hi>I may be,</hi> that <hi>thou mayeſt be,</hi> that <hi>he may be,</hi> that <hi>we may be,</hi> that <hi>ye may be,</hi> that <hi>they may be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Imperfect Subjunctive, that <hi>I might be,</hi> that <hi>thou might'ſt be,</hi> that <hi>he might be,</hi> that <hi>we might be,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>ye might be,</hi> that <hi>they might be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perfect Subjunctive, that <hi>I might have been,</hi> that <hi>thou might'ſt have been,</hi> that <hi>he might have been, that we might have been,</hi> that <hi>ye might have been,</hi> that <hi>they might have been.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:65531:42"/>
               <p>Pluperfect Subjurctive, that <hi>I might had been,</hi> that <hi>thou might'ſt had been,</hi> that <hi>he might bad been,</hi> that <hi>we might had been,</hi> that <hi>ye might had been,</hi> that <hi>they might had been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Future Subjunctive, that <hi>I may have been,</hi> that <hi>thou mayeſt have been,</hi> that <hi>he may have been, that we may have been,</hi> that <hi>ye may have been, that they may have been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Imperative, <hi>be thou, be he,</hi> or <hi>let him be; be ye, be they,</hi> or <hi>let them be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Preſent Infinitive, <hi>to be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Perfect Infinitive, <hi>to have been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Peſent Participle, <hi>being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Preter Participle, <hi>been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note. <hi>Be</hi> and <hi>beeſt</hi> are often uſed in the Preſent Tenſe, eſpecially after ſome Conjunction, as, <hi>if thou beeſt, tho we be.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Does not the preſent tenſe of the Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Verb</hi> am, <hi>with the preter participle, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times denote the perfect tenſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In External or Corporeal Actions, the preſent tenſe of the Subſtantive Verb <hi>am,</hi> with the preter participle, denotes the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect tenſe immediately paſt; as, <hi>the Letter is Written:</hi> but when we would be underſtood of the preſent tenſe paſſive in External Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we uſually expreſs it by the Subſtantive Verb, with <hi>a,</hi> for <hi>in,</hi> before the preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiple, as <hi>the Letter is a Writing;</hi> which form
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65531:42"/>of ſpeaking is uſual in all other tenſes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actively or paſſively underſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſenſe, as <hi>I was a Writing my Letter,</hi> is the imperfect active, but <hi>the Letter was a Writing,</hi> is the imperfect paſſive.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Vowel</hi> e, <hi>often left out in ſome terminations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Vowel <hi>e,</hi> is often left out in the terminations, <hi>en, ed, eſt, eth,</hi> either for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity or eaſineſs of Pronounciation, and we always put an <hi>Apoſtroph</hi> over the place of the Vowel left out, if the word be commonly uſed with it; as for Example, we write <hi>prov'd</hi> with an <hi>Apoſtroph,</hi> becauſe <hi>proved</hi> is in common uſe, but if the word be not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſed with the Vowel, we do not mark it with an <hi>Apòstroph,</hi> as in <hi>doth, doſt ſlain, done, gone,</hi> becauſe <hi>doeth doeſt, ſlaien, doen, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi> are not in common uſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the Vowel</hi> e, <hi>be left out after</hi> c, <hi>or</hi> g, <hi>ſoft?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Vowel <hi>e,</hi> be left out after <hi>c,</hi> or <hi>g,</hi> ſoft, the <hi>Apoſtroph</hi> muſt always be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, leaſt <hi>c,</hi> or <hi>g,</hi> ſoft, ſhould ſeem to be <hi>hard,</hi> as in <hi>forc't, chang'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an</hi> Apoſtroph?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>Apoſtroph</hi> is a mark put over the place of a Vowel, left out in a word for brevity or eaſineſs of Pronounciation.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:65531:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> In all Engliſh words that end in <hi>en,</hi> we pronounce the Vowel <hi>e,</hi> ſo ſwiftly, that it is ſcarce heard, as in <hi>Oxen, Chicken, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are there not ſome Defective Verbs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are ſome <hi>Defective Verbs,</hi> that neither admit the Auxiliaries before them, nor have any participles derived of them, as theſe neuter Verbs <hi>can, may, muſt, ought,</hi> and ſome others: <hi>can, canſt</hi> in the preſent tenſe, <hi>could</hi> in the Imperfect, <hi>could have</hi> in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>could had</hi> in the pluperfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can,</hi> denotes <hi>ſtrength</hi> or <hi>ability,</hi> and may in all tenſes be reſolved by the Verb <hi>am,</hi> and the Adjective <hi>able,</hi> as <hi>I can,</hi> or, <hi>I am able; I could, or I was able,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May, may'ſt</hi> in the preſent tenſe; <hi>might</hi> in the <hi>imperfect, might have</hi> in the perfect, <hi>might had</hi> in the pluperfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May,</hi> denotes either the <hi>Lawfulneſs,</hi> or <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility</hi> of a thing, and may be reſolved in all tenſes by the Subſtantive Verb, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>poſſible,</hi> as I <hi>may,</hi> or <hi>it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for me,</hi> or <hi>it is poſſible for me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſt</hi> in the preſent tenſe; in the perfect <hi>must have,</hi> in the pluperfect, <hi>muſt had.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſt,</hi> may be ſupply'd in all tenſes, by the Subſtantive Verb, and the Adjective <hi>neceſſary;</hi> as <hi>I muſt,</hi> or <hi>it is neceſſary for me,</hi> in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect <hi>it was neceſſary for me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65531:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ought to</hi> in the preſent tenſe, <hi>ought to have</hi> in the perfect, <hi>ought to had</hi> in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ought,</hi> denotes <hi>Duty,</hi> and may be ſupply'd in all tenſes by the Subſtantive Verb and the word <hi>Duty,</hi> as <hi>I ought to read,</hi> or <hi>it is my Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to read,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Should</hi> in the imperfect tenſe, <hi>ſhould have</hi> in the perfect, <hi>ſhould had</hi> in the pluperfect, <hi>ſhall have</hi> in the future.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Should,</hi> does ſometimes denote <hi>Duty</hi> as <hi>I ſhould read,</hi> and ſometimes only the <hi>future</hi> tenſe, as <hi>if I ſhould neglect to read, my Father would be angry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Would</hi> in the imperfect tenſe <hi>would have</hi> in the perfect, <hi>would had</hi> in the pluperfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Would</hi> denotes futurity, and a <hi>propenſion</hi> of the will alſo.</p>
               <p>The Verb <hi>behoveth,</hi> or <hi>behooves</hi> is only ſaid in the third Perſon ſingular and ſignifies <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite,</hi> and it has always the Adjective <hi>it</hi> before it, and an Infinitive after it, as <hi>it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooveth me to read,</hi> or <hi>it is requiſite for me to read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The <hi>Grammarians</hi> call thoſe Verbs <hi>imperſonal,</hi> that are only ſaid in the third Perſon ſingular, and they have always <hi>it</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and an Infinitive or a ſentence after them.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:65531:44"/>
               <head>Of the <hi>Particles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q <hi>What is a</hi> Particle?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Particle</hi> is a word that ſignifies the <hi>manner, Circumſtance,</hi> or <hi>Connexion</hi> of Verbs, as <hi>ſwiftly, fooliſhly with, as,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>How may one know a</hi> Particle?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Any word that can neither be declin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor congulated in a good ſenſe is a Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. As for Example, the word <hi>wiſely;</hi> for if I ſay, <hi>wiſely,</hi> of <hi>wiſely,</hi> to <hi>wiſely,</hi> with <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> or <hi>I wiſely, thou wiſelieſt, he wiſelieth,</hi> it is all nonſenſe, by which I know it is a Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of Particles are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are three ſorts of Particles; <hi>Adverbs, Prepoſitions</hi> and <hi>Conjunctions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of an Adverb.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Adverb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dverb is a Particle that denotes the manner or quality of an Action, as <hi>wiſely, ſlowly, ſadly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may one know an Adverb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Any Particle that makes compleat ſenſe with one Verb is an <hi>Adverb:</hi> As for Example, <hi>a fool ſpeaks fooliſhly, a good Man lives happily.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:65531:44"/>
               <head>Of a Prepoſition.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Prepoſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Prepoſition</hi> is a Particle that denotes ſome <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of an Action, as <hi>to, for, with, from, in, by,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may one know a Prepoſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Any Particle that makes compleat ſenſe with a Verb or Participle before it, and an <hi>oblique</hi> Caſe after it, is a Prepoſition: As for Example, I know the Particle <hi>to</hi> is a Prepoſition, becauſe I can ſay in good ſenſe, <hi>I ſpeak</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> not, <hi>I ſpeak</hi> to <hi>he,</hi> becauſe <hi>he</hi> is not an <hi>oblique</hi> Caſe; but a Nominative, with which no Prepoſition can make ſenſe: <hi>He came from me,</hi> not, <hi>from I,</hi> he was <hi>with thee,</hi> not, <hi>with thou; I ſpoke with her,</hi> not, <hi>with ſhe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Caſes are called oblique?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the the Caſes are called oblique, except the Nominative and Vocative, which are called <hi>direct</hi> Caſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Conjunction.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Conjunction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Conjunction</hi> is a Particle that joins two ſentences together: As for Example, <hi>and, as, when, that,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:65531:45"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may one know a Conjunction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every Particle that leaves the ſenſe imperfect without two Verbs is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How do you know the Particle</hi> as <hi>is a Conjunction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I know the Particle <hi>as</hi> is a Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe it leaves the ſenſe imperfect with one Verb. As for Example, <hi>As I went to School,</hi> where the ſenſe is imperfect, and the mind in ſuſpence till another Verb, or (which is the ſame) another ſentence be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, thus, <hi>As I went to School I met my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the ſame word ſometimes of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Parts of Speech?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sometimes the ſame word is of differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Parts of Speech, which muſt be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the ſenſe. As for Example, the word <hi>ſound</hi> in this ſentence (<hi>I will</hi> ſound <hi>the Trumpet</hi>) it is a Verb: In this ſentence <hi>(I hear the ſound of the Trumpet)</hi> it is a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive: In this ſentence (<hi>he is a Man of a</hi> ſound <hi>Judgment</hi>) it is an Adjective.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Abbreviatures.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are there not ſome words that are Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviatures of two or three Parts of Speech?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are ſome words that are <hi>Abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viatures</hi> of two or three Parts of Speech,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65531:45"/>which the Grammarians call <hi>Adverbs</hi> of <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe Abbreviatures called <hi>Adverbs</hi> of time, are chiefly theſe; <hi>now</hi> at this time, <hi>then</hi> at that time, <hi>when</hi> at what time or at which time, <hi>always</hi> at every time, <hi>evermore</hi> at all times, <hi>often</hi> at many times, <hi>once</hi> at one time, <hi>twice</hi> at two times, <hi>thrice</hi> at three times, <hi>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> at few times, <hi>ever</hi> at any time or at all times, <hi>never</hi> at no time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe Abbreviatures called <hi>Adverbs</hi> of <hi>place,</hi> are chiefly theſe; <hi>here</hi> in this place, <hi>there</hi> in that place, <hi>where</hi> in what place or in which place, <hi>hence</hi> from this place, <hi>thence</hi> from that place, <hi>whence</hi> from what place or from which place, <hi>hither</hi> to this place, <hi>thither</hi> to that place, <hi>whither</hi> to what place or to which place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Abbreviatures <hi>here, there, where,</hi> are often Compounded with a Prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, as <hi>hereof</hi> of this thing, <hi>thereof</hi> of that thing, <hi>whereof</hi> of what thing, or of which thing, <hi>wherein</hi> in what thing, or in which thing, <hi>herein</hi> in this thing, <hi>therein</hi> in that thing, <hi>wherewith</hi> with what thing, <hi>thereto</hi> to that thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what Caſe are the Abbreviatures of time and place?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe Abbreviatures that may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by the Prepoſitions <hi>at, in,</hi> or <hi>from,</hi> are all of the ablative Caſe.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:65531:46"/>
               <p>Thoſe Abbreviatures that may be reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Prepoſition <hi>to,</hi> or <hi>unto,</hi> are all of the Accuſative Caſe.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note, Here</hi> doth ſometimes ſignify, <hi>in this State</hi> or <hi>Condition. Whence</hi> doth ſometimes ſignify, <hi>from that Perſon,</hi> or <hi>from which Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where, here</hi> and <hi>there</hi> are Vulgarly ſaid, for <hi>whither, hither</hi> and <hi>thither,</hi> as, <hi>where are you going,</hi> for <hi>whither are you going? I am going there,</hi> for <hi>I am going thither. I came here,</hi> for <hi>I came hither.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Interjections.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are thoſe Voices called Interjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe Voices call'd Interjections are not properly words, becauſe they do not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify by the <hi>cuſtom</hi> of any Language, but are Natural Expreſſions or Signs of the Paſſions of the mind, and are the ſame in all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, as <hi>ah, o, oh, ha, ha, he,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is an Interjection ſo called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Interjection is ſo called, becauſe it is thrown in between words in ſpeaking; by the Force or Violence of ſome Paſſion, as of <hi>Joy</hi> or <hi>Grief, Pain</hi> or <hi>Pleaſure, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> or <hi>Indignation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:65531:46"/>
               <head>Of Derivative Words.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of derived Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are ſeven more uſual ſorts of derived Subſtantives, <hi>viz. Diminitive</hi> Nouns, <hi>Abſtract</hi> Nouns, Verbal Subſtantives of the <hi>Actor,</hi> Verbal Subſtantives of the <hi>Action;</hi> Nouns that ſignify <hi>Office,</hi> Nouns that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy <hi>Dominion</hi> or <hi>Rule,</hi> and Nouns that ſignify <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Condition.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Diminitive Nouns.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Diminitive Noun?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Diminitive</hi> Noun is, that which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the ſame as its Primitive Subſtantive, with the Adjective <hi>little,</hi> as <hi>Cockrel</hi> a <hi>little Cock, goſling</hi> a <hi>little Gooſe, parcel</hi> a <hi>little part,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Diminitive Nouns formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Diminitive</hi> Nouns are variouſly form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but more uſually they end in <hi>ock, kin,</hi> or <hi>et;</hi> as <hi>Hillock</hi> a <hi>little hill, Bullock</hi> a <hi>little Bull; Manikin</hi> a <hi>little Man, Willkin</hi> a <hi>little Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, Pocket</hi> a <hi>little Poke, Billet</hi> a <hi>little Bill.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65531:47"/>
               <head>Of Abſtract Nouns.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the ſame Quality both a Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and an Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſame <hi>Quality</hi> is both a Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and an Adjective, in different reſpects and under different forms; in the <hi>Abſtract,</hi> (or as it is conceiv'd without the Subject) it is a Subſtantive; in the <hi>Concrete,</hi> (or as it is joined with the Subject or Subſtantive) it is an Adjective: As for Example, <hi>kindneſs, goodneſs, meekneſs,</hi> are Subſtantives, but <hi>kind, good, meek,</hi> are Adjectives.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Abſtract Noun?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>Abſtract</hi> Noun is a Subſtantive de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived of an Adjective, and ſignifies a <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> as Abſtracted or ſeparated from any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Abſtract Subſtantives form'd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Abſtract Subſtantives</hi> are regularly formed by adding the termination <hi>neſs,</hi> to the Adjective, as <hi>goodneſs, kindneſs;</hi> and ſometimes they end in <hi>th,</hi> as <hi>length</hi> from <hi>long, ſtrength</hi> from <hi>ſtrong, wealth</hi> from <hi>weal.</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract Nouns borrowed from the Latin end variouſly, as <hi>Juſtice, Fortitude, Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:65531:47"/>
               <head>Of the Subſtantive of the Actor or Doer.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Subſtantive of the Actor or Doer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Subſtantive of the <hi>Actor</hi> or <hi>Doer,</hi> is derived of a Verb, and Denotes the <hi>uſe</hi> or <hi>habit</hi> of doing, as a <hi>reader, he that reads often,</hi> or <hi>uſeth to read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Subſtantive of the Actor or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Subſtantive of the <hi>Actor</hi> or <hi>Doer,</hi> is regularly formed in Engliſh, by adding the termination <hi>er,</hi> to the theam of the Verb; as <hi>teach, teacher; play, player:</hi> But in words borrowed from the Latin we uſually keep the Latin termination <hi>or,</hi> as <hi>Doctor,</hi> not <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> yet ſome write <hi>our</hi> for <hi>or,</hi> to avoid the Latin termination, as <hi>Governour</hi> for <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Oratour</hi> for <hi>Orator.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Subſtantive of the Action.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Subſtantive of the Action?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Subſtantive of the <hi>Action,</hi> is that which ſignifies the <hi>Action,</hi> as ſeparated from the <hi>Agent</hi> or <hi>Doer,</hi> as <hi>Learning, Reading, Writing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:65531:48"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Subſtantive of the Action formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Subſtantive of the <hi>Action</hi> is regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly formed in Engliſh, by adding the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination <hi>ing,</hi> to the theam of the Verb, as <hi>Preach, Preaching; Pray, Praying; Sing, Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and ſometimes it is the theam of the Verb taken Subſtantively, as a <hi>Command,</hi> a <hi>Dance, Love, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe:</hi> Some end in <hi>ment, age, ance,</hi> as <hi>Commandment, Tillage, Appearance;</hi> and many derived from the Latin end in <hi>ion,</hi> as <hi>Inſtruction, Correction;</hi> and many other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as <hi>Lecture, Reaſon, Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Verbal Subſtantive in</hi> ing, <hi>diſtinguiſhed from the Verbal Adjective in</hi> ing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Verbal Subſtantive in <hi>ing,</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the Verbal Adjective in <hi>ing,</hi> by the ſenſe.</p>
               <p>The Subſtantive in <hi>ing,</hi> admits <hi>a,</hi> or <hi>the,</hi> or any other Adjective before it in good ſenſe, without another Subſtantive: But the Adjective in <hi>ing,</hi> does not admit <hi>a,</hi> or <hi>the,</hi> or any other Adjective in good ſenſe, without ſome Subſtantive before it, or after it: As for Example, <hi>a Boy Singing Pſalms,</hi> here <hi>Singing</hi> is an Adjective: The <hi>Singing</hi> of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> here <hi>Singing</hi> is a Subſtantive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:65531:48"/>
               <head>Of Subſtantives that ſignify Office.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Nouns that ſignify Office formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nouns that ſignify Office are uſually formed by adding <hi>ſhip</hi> to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Primitive Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive, as <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> the <hi>Office of a King; Stewardſhip,</hi> the <hi>Office of a Steward; Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſhip,</hi> the <hi>Office of a Guardian.</hi> Some Nouns in <hi>ſhip</hi> ſignify <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Condition,</hi> as <hi>Lordſhip</hi> the <hi>State</hi> of a <hi>Lord; Partnerſhip,</hi> the <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> of <hi>Partners.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Subſtantive that ſignify Dominion.</head>
               <p>Q <hi>How are Nouns that ſignify Dominion or Rule formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nouns that ſignify <hi>Dominion</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> are uſually formed by adding <hi>dom</hi> to the Subſtantive, as <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> the <hi>Dominion</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Dominion</hi> of a <hi>King; Popedom,</hi> the <hi>Dominion</hi> of the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Subſtantives that ſignify State or Condition.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Nouns that ſignify State or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:65531:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nouns that ſignify <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> are uſually formed by adding <hi>head</hi> or <hi>hood</hi> to the Primitive Subſtantive, as the <hi>Godhead,</hi> the <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Majeſty of God: Manhood,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> or <hi>condition of a Man: Childhood,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> or <hi>condition of a Child: Brotherhood,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> or <hi>condition of Brothers: Widowhood,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> or <hi>condition of a Widow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Derivative Adjectives.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of derivative Adjectives are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The moſt uſual derivative Adjectives are of ſeven ſorts, <hi>viz. poſſeſſive</hi> Adjectives, <hi>material</hi> Adjectives, Adjectives of <hi>fulneſs,</hi> Adjectives of <hi>emptineſs,</hi> Adjectives of <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> diminutive <hi>Adjectives,</hi> and <hi>ordinal</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Poſſeſſive Adjective.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a poſſeſſive Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>poſſeſſive</hi> Adjective is nothing elſe but the Genitive of the Poſſeſſor under the form of an Adjective, and the Subſtantive after it is always the poſſeſſed Subſtantive; for there cannot be a Poſſeſſor without ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing poſſeſſed, nor any thing poſſeſſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Poſſeſſor.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:65531:49"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a poſſeſſive Adjective formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>poſſeſſive</hi> Adjective is variouſly form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but for the moſt part it is made in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh by adding <hi>s</hi> or <hi>es</hi> poſſeſſive to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive, and oftentimes <hi>s</hi> or <hi>es</hi> is omitted for the conveniency of pronunciation, as the <hi>houſe Door</hi> for the <hi>houſes Door,</hi> the <hi>horſes Bridles</hi> for the <hi>horſeſes Bridles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know a poſſeſſive Adjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is always a <hi>poſſeſſive</hi> Adjective that may in good ſenſe be reſolved by the Genitive of its Primitive, made by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition <hi>of;</hi> as, <hi>my</hi> or <hi>of me, thy</hi> or <hi>of thee, our</hi> or <hi>of us, your</hi> or <hi>of you, his</hi> or <hi>of him, her</hi> or <hi>of her, their</hi> or <hi>of them; Engliſh</hi> or <hi>of England, French</hi> or <hi>of France, Italian</hi> or <hi>of Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Does not an Adjective admit</hi> s <hi>or</hi> es <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Adjective taken ſubſtantively ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits <hi>s</hi> or <hi>es</hi> poſſeſſive, as <hi>another's Debt,</hi> or the <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note.</hi> When the poſſeſſed Subſtantive is not expreſs'd after <hi>my, thy, our, your, her, their,</hi> we ſay <hi>mine, thine ours, yours, hers, theirs;</hi> as, <hi>this Book is mine,</hi> not <hi>this Book is my; this Pen is thine,</hi> not <hi>this Pen is thy.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the uſe of a poſſeſſive Adjective, ſince it is nothing elſe but a Subſtantive of the Genitive Caſe, under the form of an Adjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:65531:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Tho the poſſeſſive Adjective be a real Subſtantive of the Genitive Caſe, yet it is of great uſe to diſtinguiſh the Genitive of the <hi>Poſſeſſor</hi> from other Genitives made by the prepoſition <hi>of,</hi> which is often very ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous and doubtful.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Material Adjective.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a material Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>material</hi> Adjective is that which denotes the <hi>matter</hi> of which any thing is made; and in Engliſh it is uſually made by adding <hi>en</hi> to the Subſtantive, and ſometimes <hi>en</hi> is omitted, as <hi>a golden Ring,</hi> or a <hi>gold Ring,</hi> or a <hi>Ring made</hi> of <hi>Gold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know a material Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is always a <hi>material</hi> Adjective that may in good ſenſe be reſolved by the <hi>Primitive Subſtantive,</hi> the participle <hi>made,</hi> and the prepoſition <hi>of;</hi> as <hi>brazen</hi> or <hi>made of Braſs, wooden</hi> or <hi>made of Wood, woolen</hi> or <hi>made of Wool, flaxen</hi> or <hi>made of Flax.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of an Adjective of Fulneſs.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Adjective of fulneſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Adjective of <hi>fulneſs</hi> is that which denotes the <hi>plenty, frequency</hi> or <hi>fulneſs</hi> of a thing or action, and it is uſually made in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65531:50"/>Engliſh by adding the termination <hi>y</hi> or <hi>ous</hi> to the Subſtantive, and ſometimes the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective <hi>full,</hi> as <hi>healthy</hi> or <hi>healthful,</hi> or <hi>full of Health.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know an Adjective of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is always an Adjective of <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that may be reſolved in good ſenſe by the primitive Subſtantive, and the Adjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>full,</hi> as <hi>witty</hi> or <hi>full of Wit, malicious</hi> or <hi>full of Malice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Adjectives of Emptineſs.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Adjective of emptineſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Adjective of <hi>emptineſs</hi> is that which ſignifies the <hi>want</hi> of the <hi>thing,</hi> and it is formed in Engliſh by adding <hi>leſs</hi> to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive, as <hi>healthleſs</hi> or <hi>without Health, grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> or <hi>void of Grace, ſenſeleſs</hi> or <hi>void of Senſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Adjectives of Likeneſs.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Adjective of likeneſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Adjective of <hi>likeneſs</hi> is that which denotes <hi>likeneſs to a thing,</hi> and it is uſually formed in Engliſh by adding the terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>ly</hi> to the Subſtantive, and ſometimes the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65531:51"/>Adjective <hi>like,</hi> as <hi>godly</hi> or <hi>like God, manly</hi> or <hi>like a Man,</hi> or <hi>manlike.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Diminutive Adjectives.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a diminutive Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A diminutive Adjective is that which denotes a <hi>little</hi> or <hi>ſomewhat</hi> of the nature or quality of the thing, and it is uſually form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Engliſh by adding the termination <hi>iſh</hi> to a Subſtantive or Adjective, as <hi>Childiſh</hi> or <hi>ſomewhat</hi> of <hi>a Child, blackiſh,</hi> a <hi>little black,</hi> or <hi>ſomewhat black;</hi> and ſometimes it is made by adding the Adjective <hi>ſome,</hi> as <hi>troubleſome, handſome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Ordinal Adjectives.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Adjectives of Number diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Adjectives of <hi>number</hi> are diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Cardinal</hi> and <hi>Ordinal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Cardinal Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Cardinal</hi> Adjective, or an Adjective of the <hi>cardinal Number,</hi> is that which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>Number,</hi> as <hi>one, two, three, four, five, ſix, ſeven eight, nine, ten,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Ordinal Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:65531:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>Ordinal</hi> Adjective is formed from the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> and ſignifies the <hi>order</hi> and <hi>place</hi> of the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> as, <hi>firſt, ſecond, third fourth, fifth, ſixth, ſeventh, eighth, ninth, tenth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus, <hi>firſt</hi> is the foremoſt of any number, <hi>ſecond</hi> the latter of <hi>two, third</hi> the laſt of <hi>three, fourth</hi> the laſt of <hi>four, fifth</hi> the laſt of <hi>five,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Derivative Verbs.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are derivative Verbs formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Derivative</hi> Verbs, are uſually formed from Subſtantives and Adjectives, by add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a verbal termination to the Subſtantive or Adjective, as <hi>ſhip, I ſhip, thou ſhippeſt, he ſhippeth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to put into a Ship;</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are formed by adding the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination <hi>en</hi> to the Subſtantive or Adjective, as <hi>lengthen</hi> to <hi>make long, ſhorten</hi> to <hi>make ſhort, widen</hi> to <hi>make wide,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Derivative Adverbs.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of derivative Adverbs are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are four more uſual ſorts of <hi>derivative</hi> Adverbs, <hi>viz. Poſitive, Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, Superlative,</hi> and <hi>Ordinal</hi> Adverbs.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Poſitive Adverb formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:65531:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Poſitive</hi> Adverb is uſually formed by adding the termination <hi>ly</hi> to the Poſitive Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective, as <hi>wiſe, wiſely; fooliſh, fooliſhly; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſinfully,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>How may a Poſitive Adverb be reſolved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Poſitive</hi> Adverb may be reſolved by the Prepoſition <hi>in,</hi> with the Ablative <hi>manner,</hi> and its Poſitive adjective, as <hi>ignorantly,</hi> or <hi>in an ignorant manner; fooliſhly,</hi> or <hi>in a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not ſome Poſitive Adverbs the ſame as their poſitive Adjectives?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Some <hi>poſitive</hi> Adverbs are the ſame as their <hi>poſitive</hi> Adjectives, as <hi>ill, little, much;</hi> not <hi>illy, littlely;</hi> ſo <hi>well,</hi> not <hi>welly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>How are Comparative and Superlative Adverbs formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Comparative</hi> and <hi>Superlative</hi> Adverbs are nothing elſe but Comparative and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Adjectives, taken adverbially with Verbs and Participles; and for the moſt part they may be reſolved by a poſitive Adverb with the Particles <hi>more, moſt,</hi> or <hi>very;</hi> as <hi>I write ſlower</hi> or <hi>more ſlowly:</hi> Solomon <hi>ſpoke wiſeſt</hi> or <hi>moſt wiſely</hi> of all Men.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are Ordinal Adverbs formed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ordinal</hi> Adverbs are uſually formed by adding <hi>ly</hi> to the Ordinal Adjective, and they may be reſolved by the Prepoſition <hi>in,</hi> with the Ablative <hi>place,</hi> and the Ordinal Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective; as <hi>ſecondly,</hi> or <hi>in the ſecond place; thirdly,</hi> or <hi>in the third place; fourthly,</hi> or <hi>in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65531:52"/>the fourth place. Firſt</hi> is both an Ordinal Adjective, and an Ordinal Adverb; for we do not ſay <hi>firſtly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the inſeparable Particles <hi>un, dis,</hi> and <hi>mis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why are the Particles</hi> un, dis, <hi>and</hi> mis, <hi>call'd</hi> inſeparable?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Particles <hi>un, did,</hi> and <hi>mis,</hi> are call'd <hi>inſeparable,</hi> becauſe they are never uſed but in compoſition with other words; and they all include the negative Particle <hi>not,</hi> beſides their peculiar ſignification.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What does the Particle</hi> un <hi>ſignify?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Particle <hi>un</hi> always ſignifies <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> that is the abſence or want of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that either was or ought to be; as, <hi>unmerciful unkind, unholy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Does not the Particle</hi> in <hi>ſometimes ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify</hi> un?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In words derived from the Latin, the Particle <hi>in</hi> (or <hi>im</hi> when the pronunciation requires it) is the ſame as the privative Particle <hi>un;</hi> as <hi>ingratitude</hi> or <hi>unthankfulneſs, impatience</hi> or <hi>want of Patience:</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is an <hi>intenſive</hi> Particle, and then it ſignifies <hi>very</hi> or <hi>very much;</hi> as <hi>intent</hi> or <hi>very earneſt; inraged</hi> or <hi>very much provoked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the French Particle</hi> en <hi>ſometimes uſed for the Latin Particle</hi> in?</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:65531:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In many words borrowed from French and Latin, we uſe the French Particle <hi>en</hi> for <hi>in,</hi> when it is not privative: thus we indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently ſay <hi>enraged</hi> or <hi>inraged, engrave</hi> or <hi>ingrave, engender</hi> or <hi>ingender, embrace</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, employ</hi> or <hi>imploy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Particle <hi>un</hi> is always <hi>privative, en</hi> never, <hi>in</hi> ſometimes <hi>privative</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not: yet in Verbs it is ſeldom ever privative, but often in Participles and other words.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What does the Particle</hi> dis <hi>ſignify?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Particle <hi>dis</hi> uſually ſignifies ſome <hi>contrariety,</hi> as <hi>to diſhonour,</hi> or <hi>do ſomething contrary to ones honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What does the Particle</hi> mis <hi>ſignify?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Particle <hi>mis</hi> uſually ſignifies <hi>wrong</hi> or <hi>error,</hi> as to <hi>miſtake</hi> or <hi>take wrong,</hi> or <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than it is; to miſuſe,</hi> or <hi>uſe ill,</hi> or <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than we ought.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a SENTENCE.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Sentence is a conſtruction of words wherein ſomething is ſaid of another, as <hi>man is Mortal;</hi> here it is ſaid of <hi>Man</hi> that <hi>he is Mortal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the eſſential parts of a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:65531:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The eſſential parts of a Sentence, without which it cannot be, are a Verb and the Nominative of the Subject; all other words in a Sentence depend upon one of theſe two mediately or immediately.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why cannot a Sentence be without a Verb and a Nominative Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Sentence cannot be without a Verb and a Nominative Caſe, becauſe nothing can be ſaid of another without a Verb, and no Verb can be without the Nominative of the Subject either expreſt or underſtood.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Sentence diſtingniſhed in reſpect of Compoſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Sentence in reſpect of Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Simple</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a ſimple Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſimple Sentence is that wherein there is but one Verb and one Nominative of the Subject, either expreſt or underſtood.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Compound Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Compound Sentence is two ſimple Sentences joined together by a Conjunctive Particle, or a Conjunctive Adjective, as <hi>I read, and thou playeſt: This is the Boy who broke the Windows.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:65531:54"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Syntax or Conſtruction of words in a Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Syntax?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Syntax or Conſtruction is the right joining of words in a Sentence.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What's the conſtruction of the Adjective with its Subſtantive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Adjective is always of the ſame Gender, Number and Caſe with its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive; as <hi>this Man, that Boy, every Book, all things, one day;</hi> not <hi>thoſe Man, thoſe Boy, every Books, all thing, one days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> Tho Engliſh Adjectives for the moſt part have no diſtinction of Gender, Number or Caſe, yet ſome have, as in the inſtances above, and many more: on which Account this Rule cannot well be omitted in Engliſh.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Appoſition.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Appoſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Appoſition is the adding of one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive to another, to declare and explain it: the latter or explaining Subſtantive is called the <hi>Appoſite</hi> Subſtantive; the former or explained Subſtantive is called the <hi>ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent</hi> Subſtantive: as for Example, if I ſay Paul <hi>the Apoſtle,</hi> the Appoſite Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65531:54"/>
                  <hi>Apoſtle</hi> explains what <hi>Paul</hi> I ſpeak of; and if I ſay the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> the Appoſite Subſtantive <hi>Paul</hi> declares what <hi>Apoſtle</hi> I mean.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the conſtruction of the Appoſite with its Antecedent Subſtantive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Appoſite</hi> Subſtantive is always of the ſame Caſe with its <hi>Antecedent</hi> Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as <hi>my Father loves me his only Child.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Nominative of the Subject.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Nominative of the Subject?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Nominative of the Subject is that of which the Verb is predicated or ſaid; and it uſually comes before the Verb.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Muſt every Verb have a Nominative of the Subject?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every Verb muſt have a Nominative of the Subject either expreſt or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, becauſe there can be no Action with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Agent, nor Paſſion without a Patient, nor Being without ſomething that is in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the conſtruction of the Verb with the Nominative of the Subject?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Verb is always of the ſame Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Perſon with the Nominative of the Subject, as <hi>I write, thou writeſt, he writeth;</hi> not <hi>I writeſt, thou writeth. I am, thou art, he is, we are;</hi> not <hi>I art, thou am, he are.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:65531:55"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not a whole Sentence be the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native Caſe to a Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A whole Sentence is often taken as one aggregate Subſtantive of the Neuter Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and third Perſon ſingular; and then it may be the Nominative Caſe before a Verb, or the Accuſative after it, a Subſtantive to an Adjective, or an Antecedent to a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: as for Example, <hi>He who is vertuous is content with his Condition, which is the true property of Riches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When does the Nominative of the Subject come after the Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Nominative of the Subject uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally comes after the Verb, or after its auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary, when the Sentence is imperative or interrogative; as <hi>read thou,</hi> or <hi>do thou read, readeſt thou,</hi> or <hi>doſt thou read?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> When a declarative or final Sentence is the Nominative Caſe, it uſually comes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Verb, and then the Adjective <hi>it</hi> comes before the Verb; as for example, <hi>It grieves me much that thou art idle,</hi> or <hi>that thou art idle grieves me much.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> When the Nominative is put inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely, it uſually comes after the Verb, and then we put the indefinite Particle <hi>there</hi> before it; as <hi>there came a Man to our Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Nominative of the Subject ſometimes ſuppreſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Nominative of the Subject is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuppreſt after the ſecond Perſon Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65531:55"/>and Plural of the Imperative; as <hi>go,</hi> for <hi>go thou,</hi> or <hi>go ye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> Before Verbs of Nature, and then we put <hi>it</hi> before the Verb; as <hi>it rains, it grows Night.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Nominative of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Nominative of the Predicate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Nominative of the Predicate is that which is ſaid of the Nominative of the Subject; as <hi>I am he, thou art ſhe, thoſe are they;</hi> not <hi>I am him, thou art her, thoſe are them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not the Nominative come after other Verbs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Nominative may come after any other Verb, by a ſuppreſſion of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive Verb or its Participles.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>After what Verbs does the Nominative moſt uſually come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Nom. comes moſt uſually after intranſitive Verbs, and Paſſive Verbs, of calling, eſteeming, judging, and others; which therefore may improperly be called copulative Verbs; as <hi>I am called</hi> Peter: <hi>thou art eſteemed (to be) an honeſt Man: My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther returned (being) angry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know when a Subſtantive or Adjective that comes after a Verb is in the Nom. Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:65531:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When a Subſtantive or Adjective comes after any Verb, it is in the Nom. Caſe, if it belong to the Nom. before the Verb; as <hi>I went to bed ſick,</hi> or <hi>being ſick; the Child died young,</hi> or <hi>being young.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may one know the Nom. of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate from the Nom. of the Subject?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In order of nature, the Nom. of the Predicate comes after the copulative Verb; but oftentimes the natural order of Predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is changed, by which the ſenſe and meaning of Authors is often miſtaken and perverted. Yet the Predicate may be eaſily known from the Subject, whether it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after the Verb, becauſe it is always a ſuperior or more common Subſtantive than the Subject, or at leaſt equal to it, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver inferior or leſs common.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know the ſuperior Subſtantive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is always the ſuperior Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive that can in good ſenſe be affirmed of the inferior and of more things, but not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wiſe. Thus all common Nouns are ſuperior to the perſonal Subſtantives <hi>I</hi> and <hi>thou,</hi> and all proper Names, and all other individuals; and more common Nouns ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to leſs commons Nouns; as <hi>London is a City; an Oak is a Tree; a Sparrow is a Bird;</hi> not contrary wiſe, <hi>a City is</hi> London; <hi>a Tree is an Oak; a Bird is a Sparrow;</hi> becauſe there are more <hi>Citys</hi> than <hi>London,</hi> more <hi>Trees</hi> than <hi>Oaks,</hi> and more <hi>Birds</hi> than <hi>Sparrows.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:65531:56"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is the Predicate equal to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Predicate is equal to the Subject, when they can be mutually affirmed of one another, and one cannot be ſaid of more things than the other; as, <hi>every extended Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is a Body,</hi> and <hi>every Body is an extended Subſtance; every Man is a rational Creature, every rational Creature is a Man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Vocative.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the conſtruction of the Vocative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Vocative is no part of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, but only the Perſon to whom the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is addreſt, and therefore depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no other word in the Sentence.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Of what Perſon is the Vocative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Vocative is always of the ſecond Perſon, Singular or Plural.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> Perſons or intelligent Beings properly have the Vocative Caſe, becauſe they only can be ſpoken to: yet other things are ſometimes ſpoken to, as if they were Perſons, and then we give them the Vocative Caſe.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Voc. governed of the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> O?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Voc. is not governed of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terjection <hi>O,</hi> tho it be ſometimes put before the Voc. in Exclamation, as it may alſo be before any other word.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:65531:57"/>
               <head>Of the Gentive of the Poſſeſſor.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what is the Gen. of the Poſſeſſor go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Genitive of the Poſſeſſor is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned of ſome poſſeſſed Subſtantive, either expreſt or underſtood; as <hi>the Word of God; the Life of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not a poſſeſſive Adjective often ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for the Gen. of the Poſſeſſor?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Poſſeſſive Adjective being nothing elſe but the Gen. of the Poſſeſſor under the form of an Adjective, is elegantly ſubſtituted for the Gen. of its Primitive made by <hi>of,</hi> to avoid ambiguity; as, <hi>my hand,</hi> or <hi>the hand of me; God's Word,</hi> or <hi>the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The poſſeſſive Adjectives, <hi>my, thy, his, her, our, your, their,</hi> are almoſt always uſed inſtead of their Primitive Genitives made by <hi>of,</hi> when Poſſeſſion is ſignified; as <hi>my Houſe, thy Book, our Town, your Coun try;</hi> not <hi>the Houſe of me, the Book of thee, the Town of us, the Country of you.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When the Genitive of the Poſſeſſor is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in ſeveral words, where muſt</hi> s <hi>or</hi> es <hi>Poſſeſſive be added?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the Gen. of the Poſſeſſor is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in ſeveral words, they are taken as one aggregate Subſtantive, and <hi>s</hi> or <hi>es</hi> Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſive added to the laſt word; as, <hi>the King
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:65531:57"/>of</hi> England<hi>'s Court;</hi> Julius Caeſar Scaliger<hi>'s Book.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Genitive of the Object.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what is the Genitive of the Object governed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Gen. of the Object is governed of a verbal Subſtantive, of an active Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; as, <hi>the reading of the Bible, the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a Sinner, a lover of his Country.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Gen. of the Poſſeſſor, and the Gen. of the Object, are ſometimes govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the ſame verbal Subſtantive; as, <hi>God's care of his Creatures.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note, <hi>My love</hi> is that which I poſſeſs, and wherewith I love another; <hi>the love of me</hi> is that of which I am the Object, and with which another loves me.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Genitive of the greater Number.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what is the Genitive of the greater number governed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Genitive of the greater number is governed of ſome partitive Adjective; as, <hi>one of the Siſters, the beſt of the Boys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p ana="#role_note">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Genitive of the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is always Plural, except it be a collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65531:58"/>Noun; as, <hi>the beſt of the People, the worſt of the City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p ana="#role_note">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> That Partition of the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is ſometimes made by the Prepoſition <hi>among;</hi> as, <hi>the wiſeſt among them,</hi> or <hi>the wiſeſt of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Collective Noun?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Collective</hi> Noun, or a Noun of <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> Singular, is that which in the Singular number contains many Individuals; as, <hi>a Nation, a City,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Adjectives are Partitive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Almoſt all Adjectives may be uſed <hi>partitively,</hi> but eſpecially interrogative, nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meral, comparative, and ſuperlative Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Genitive of the greater Quantity.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what is the Genitive of the greater Quantity govern'd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Gen. of the greater Quantity is governed of ſome Subſtantive ſignifying a leſſer Quantity; and oftentimes an Adjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Quantity is elegantly ſubſtituted for its abſtract Subſtantive: as, <hi>a buſhel of Wheat, a yard of Cloth, a foot of Ground, part of the Mony, moſt of the Time, enough of Hail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note, <hi>the Prepoſition</hi> of <hi>is ſometimes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd; as</hi> much Wine, <hi>for</hi> a great quantity of Wine; more Wine <hi>for</hi> a greater quantity of Wine; a little Bread <hi>for</hi> a ſmall quantity of Bread.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Genitive of the greater Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity is uſually Singular, but not always; as, <hi>a barrel of Oyſters.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Genitive of the Poſſeſſor, and the Genitive of the greater Quantity, may both be governed of the ſame Subſtantive; as, <hi>my part of the Wine.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:65531:58"/>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Genitive of the Part or Property.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what is the Genitive of the Part or Property governed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the <hi>Subſtantive of the Part or Property</hi> has an Adjective joined with it, it is governed of the Subſtantive, whoſe Part or Property it is in the Genitive, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the Ablative with the Prepoſition <hi>with</hi> before it; as, <hi>a Boy of a good Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, a Man of a long Head,</hi> or <hi>with a long Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> In Engliſh the Adjective is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuppreſt, eſpecially when the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is a verbal Subſtantive; as, <hi>a man of Senſe,</hi> for <hi>a man of good Senſe.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:65531:59"/>
               <head>Of the Dative.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what is the Dative governed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Dative</hi> is governed of ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable Adjective or Verb, or of words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived of them, whether Subſtantives, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectives, or Adverbs.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Adjectives and Verbs are appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Almoſt all Adjectives and Verbs may be applied to a thing, yet ſome are of their own nature more applicable than others, as Adjectives and Verbs that denote Profit or Loſs, Good or Evil, or any other reference to a thing: as, <hi>it is agreeable to nature; he is obliged to me; be acted agreeably to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; where there is no Crime, there is no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to puniſhment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Prepoſition</hi> to <hi>ſometimes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd before the Dative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Prepoſition <hi>to</hi> or <hi>unto,</hi> is often ſuppreſt before the Dative; as, <hi>I gave him a Bock,</hi> or <hi>I gave to him a Bock; like me,</hi> or <hi>like to me; near thee,</hi> or <hi>near to thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> We uſually ſuppreſs <hi>to</hi> before the Subſtantive <hi>home;</hi> as <hi>I came home,</hi> not <hi>to home.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note, <hi>To</hi> or <hi>into,</hi> after Verbs of Motion, is a Prepoſition of the Accuſative Caſe.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:65531:59"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not</hi> for <hi>ſometimes ſubſtituted for</hi> to <hi>in Application?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. For</hi> is ſometimes ſubſtituted for <hi>to</hi> in Application; as, <hi>I have a Book for you,</hi> or <hi>to you; This is for your Profit,</hi> or <hi>to your Profit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Accuſative of the Object.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what is the Accuſative of the Object governed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Accuſative of the Object is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways governed of ſome Verb or Participle of an Active ſignification, either expreſt or underſtood; as, <hi>I call thee, I call him, I call them;</hi> not <hi>I call thou, I call he, I call they.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Accuſative of the Object ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuppreſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the Accuſative of the Object is a cognate Subſtantive, or of the ſame ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification with the Verb it is uſually ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt; as, <hi>I live,</hi> viz. <hi>a Life:</hi> but if it have an Adjective with it, it is neceſſarily expreſt; as <hi>I live a good Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Ablative.</head>
               <p>Q <hi>Of what is the Ablative governed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Ablative is always governed of ſome Prepoſition of the Ablative Caſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65531:60"/>expreſt or underſtood; as, <hi>from me, from thee;</hi> not <hi>from I, from thou.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Paſſive Verbs and Participles.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What caſe have Verbs and Participles of a Paſſive ſignification after them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Verbs and Participles of a Paſſive ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification have after them the Ablative of the Agent or Doer, with the Prepoſition <hi>of</hi> or <hi>by;</hi> as, <hi>a good Child is loved of</hi> or <hi>by his Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> There is a verbal Adjective that ends in <hi>able,</hi> and ſometimes in <hi>ible,</hi> which ſignifies a Paſſive power, and ſometimes an Active power: when it denotes a Paſſive power, it is a Paſſive Participle, and admits after it the Ablative of the Doer, with the Prepoſition <hi>of</hi> or <hi>by;</hi> as, <hi>attainable by no Man:</hi> but when it denotes an Active Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, it is not a Participle; as, <hi>a forcible Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine,</hi> or <hi>a Medicine that can force.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What's the difference betwixt Action and Paſſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Action and Paſſion are the very ſame in ſenſe, and differ only in the manner of Expreſſion: for whatever is the Object of Action, is always the ſubject of Paſſion; and contrary wiſe, whatever is the Subject of Paſſion, is the Object of Action.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:65531:60"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>May Intranſitive Verbs be ſaid in the firſt and ſecond Perſons Paſſive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Intranſitive Verbs cannot be ſaid in the firſt and ſecond Perſons Paſſive, becauſe the Object of intranſitive Verbs is only the Accuſative of their own ſignification, which is always of the third Perſon, and therefore cannot be the Nominative to the firſt and ſecond Perſons Paſſive; for nothing can be the Subject to Paſſive verbs and Participles that cannot be the Object of their Active Verbs and Participles: as for Example, I cannot ſay in good ſenſe, <hi>I am lived,</hi> in the Paſſive Voice; becauſe the perſonal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive <hi>I</hi> cannot be the Accuſative of the Object in the Active Voice; but I can ſay, <hi>a Life is lived,</hi> becauſe I can ſay in the Active Voice, <hi>I live a Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may a Sentence be changed from Active to Paſſive, the ſenſe remaining the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Sentence may be changed from Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to Paſſive, the ſenſe remaining the ſame, by turning the Accuſative of the Object af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Active Verb, into the Nominative of the Subject before the Paſſive Verb, and the Nom. of the Subject before the Active Verb into the Ablative of the Doer, with the Prepoſition <hi>of</hi> or <hi>by</hi> before it after the Paſſive Verb; as, <hi>I call thee,</hi> paſſively <hi>thou art called by me,</hi> or <hi>of me; my Father loves me,</hi> paſſively, <hi>I am loved of my Father,</hi> or <hi>by my Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:65531:61"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if there be another Accuſative af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Accuſative of the Object?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If there be another Accuſative after the Accuſative of the Object, it is either the Appoſite Accuſative by a ſuppreſſion of the Participle <hi>being,</hi> or the Accuſative of the Predicate after the copulative Infinitive <hi>to be;</hi> or it is the Accuſative of ſome Prepoſition ſuppreſt.</p>
               <p>If it be the Appoſite Accuſative, it is turned into the Nom. and put after the Nom. of the Subject before the Paſſive Verb; as, <hi>I read</hi> Paul <hi>the Apoſtle;</hi> paſſively <hi>Paul the Apoſtle is read by me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be the Accuſative of the Predicate, it is turned into the Nom. after the Paſſive Verb; as, <hi>I will make thee a Scholar;</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, <hi>you ſhall be made a Scholar by me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be the Accuſative of ſome Prepoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuppreſt, then it comes after the Paſſive Verb in the Accuſative Caſe; as, <hi>I will teach thee them;</hi> paſſively, <hi>thou ſhalt be taught them by me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Compound Sentences.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which are the principal Compound Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The principal Compound Sentences are, a <hi>Relative, Copulative, Declarative, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Continuative, Comparative,</hi> and <hi>Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Sentence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:65531:61"/>
               <head>Of a Relative Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Relative Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Relative Sentence is that which hath in it the Relative Adjective <hi>who</hi> or <hi>which.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is the Relative Adjective ſo called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Relative Adjective is ſo called, becauſe it relates or rehearſes after it ſome antecedent or foregoing Subſtantive; as, <hi>this is the Book which</hi> (Book) <hi>I loſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what Number and Perſon muſt the Relative be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Relative muſt be of the ſame Number and Perſon with the Antecedent.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may a Relative Sentence be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Relative be the Nom. of the Subject to the following Verb, then the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence may be contracted by putting away the Relative, and turning the Verb into a Participle, to which the Antecedent is the Subſtantive: as for Example, <hi>A man who wants Learning is little eſteemed;</hi> contracted, <hi>a man wanting Learning is little eſteemed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the Relative be the Accuſative of the Object to the following Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Relative be the Accuſative of the Object to the following Verb, turn it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Nom. of the Subject before the paſſive Verb: as, <hi>A man whom God hates is wretched;</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:65531:62"/>paſſively, <hi>a man who is hated of God is wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> contracted. <hi>a man hated of God is wretched.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q <hi>Into what Participle muſt the Verb be turned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Verb be active, it muſt be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the preſent Participle; but if it be Paſſive, it muſt be turned into the Preter Participle.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>What if the Relative be the Nom. to the Subſtantive Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> If the Relative be the Nom. to the Subſtantive Verb, it is turned into its Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple <hi>being,</hi> and the Predicate after the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive Verb muſt be conformed to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent Subſtantive in caſe.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> This Contraction made by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiple <hi>being,</hi> is the ground of Appoſition, and may be reſolved by the Relative and the Subſtantive Verb: but if the Appoſite Subſtantive be a proper name, it is reſolved by the Relative, and a Paſſive Verb of <hi>call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> as, <hi>Paul the Apoſtle,</hi> or <hi>Paul who is the Apoſtle; the Apoſtle</hi> Paul, or <hi>the Apoſtle who is called</hi> Paul.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Participle <hi>being</hi> is very often ſuppreſt in Engliſh, and always in Latin.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know the caſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Relative with the Antecedent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, either expreſt or underſtood, is the Nom. to the following Verb, if there come no other Nom. between it and the following
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65531:62"/>Verb; but if there come another Nom. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween it and the following Verb, then it is governed of the Verb, or of ſome other word in the Sentence with the Verb.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Is not the Antecedent uſually ſuppreſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Relative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Antecedent is uſually ſuppreſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Relative to avoid a repetition, and ſometimes is ſuppreſt before the Relative, but never both before and after.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Relative ſometimes ſuppreſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Relative is often elegantly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in Engliſh; as, <hi>this is the Child I love,</hi> or <hi>whom I love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the Relative be ſuppreſt after a Prepoſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Relative be ſuppreſt after a Prepoſition, the Prepoſition is elegantly put after the following Verb; as, <hi>this is the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whom I ſpoke,</hi> or <hi>this is the Perſon I ſpoke of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of what Perſon is a Subſtantive or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective of the firſt or ſecond Perſon affirmed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every Subſtantive or Adjective affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the firſt or ſecond Perſon, is then of the firſt or ſecond Perſon; as, <hi>I poor man am ſinging,</hi> not <hi>is ſinging; thou rich man art la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting,</hi> not <hi>is lamenting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the firſt or ſecond Perſon be the Antecedent to the Relative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the firſt or ſecond Perſon, or any other Subſtantive or Adjective affirmed of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65531:63"/>the firſt or ſecond Perſon mediately or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, be the Antecedent to a Relative of the Nom. Caſe, then the Relative and the Verb are alſo of the firſt or ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: as for Example, <hi>I am a man who am full of Grief,</hi> not <hi>who is full of Grief; Thou art a Boy who loveſt to be idle,</hi> not <hi>who loveth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not a poſſeſſive Adjective ſometimes the Antecedent to the Relative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A poſſeſſive Adjective is often the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent to the Relative; as, <hi>This is my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting who am a Scribler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> If the poſſeſſive Adjective has an Appoſite Subſtantive, Adjective, or Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is of the Genitive Caſe, and comes after the poſſeſſed Subſtantive; as, <hi>my Sin alone is incorrigible,</hi> for <hi>the Sin of me alone: No man regards his Promiſe, a perfidious Knave,</hi> for <hi>being a perfidious Knave,</hi> or <hi>who is a perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Knave.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Relative contraction reſolved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Relative contraction is reſolved by ſupplying the Relative Adjective after the antecedent Subſtantive, and turning the Participle into the Verb, and putting the appoſite Subſtantive after the Subſtantive Verb.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:65531:63"/>
               <head>Of a Copulative Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a copulative Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Copulative Sentence is that which hath in it the copulative Conjunction <hi>and.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Copulative Sentence contracted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If two coupled Subſtantives of the ſame Caſe have the ſame Verbs, the ſame Adjectives, the ſame appoſite Subſtantives, they may be turned into one Verb Plural, one Adjective Plural, and one Appoſite Plural.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the Verbs be of different Perſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Verbs be of different Perſons, the Verb Plural is of the more worthy Perſon. The firſt Perſon is more worthy than the ſecond, and the ſecond than the third; as, <hi>I and thou art Boys;</hi> here the Verb <hi>are</hi> is of the firſt Perſon Plural: <hi>thou and</hi> Peter <hi>are idle,</hi> here <hi>are</hi> is of the ſecond Perſon Plural.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the two Nominatives be the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the two Nominatives be the ſame, the latter is uſually ſuppreſt; as, Peter <hi>ſtood, and</hi> Peter <hi>prayed;</hi> contracted, Peter <hi>ſtood and prayed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> If the two Verbs be of the ſame Tenſe, one of them may be turn'd into the Preſent Participle, and then the ſenſe is the ſame as in a continuative Sentence; as, <hi>Peter
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65531:64"/>ſtood praying,</hi> or, Peter <hi>prayed ſtanding,</hi> or <hi>while he ſtood.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Declarative and Final Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Declarative Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Declarative Sentence is that which hath in it the declarative Conjunction <hi>that;</hi> as, <hi>I know that thou art he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a final Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A final Sentence is that which hath in it the final Conjunction <hi>that;</hi> as, <hi>I deſire that I may read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Declarative or Final Sentence contracted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Declarative or Final Sentence is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by putting away the Particle <hi>that,</hi> and turning the Nom. into the Accuſative, and the Verb into the Infinitive: as, <hi>I know that thou art he;</hi> contracted, <hi>I know thee to be him: I deſire that I may read;</hi> contracted, <hi>I deſire to read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Nom. of the Predicate after a copulative Verb is turned into the Accuſative after the Copulative Infinitive; becauſe the Predicate muſt always be in the ſame Caſe with the Subject; as, <hi>I know thee to be her,</hi> not <hi>to be ſhe.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the Accuſ. before the Infinitive be the ſame Subſtantive with the Nom. of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Verb?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:65531:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Accuſ. before the Infinitive be the ſame Subſtantive with the Nom. of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Verb, it is elegantly ſuppreſt; as, <hi>I deſire that I may go;</hi> contracted, <hi>I deſire to go:</hi> and if the Infinitive be Copulative, the Predicate after it is then the Nom. Caſe; as, <hi>I deſire to be he,</hi> not <hi>him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall one know when the Particle</hi> that <hi>is Declarative, and when it is Final?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Particle <hi>that</hi> is Declarative when it may in good ſenſe be ſuppreſt; as, <hi>I know that he is come,</hi> or <hi>I know he is come.</hi> It is Final when it admits after it in good ſenſe the Auxiliary <hi>may</hi> or <hi>might;</hi> as, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that thou read,</hi> or <hi>that thou may read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is the Adjective</hi> that <hi>Relative, and when Demonſtrative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Adjective <hi>that</hi> is Relative when it may in good ſenſe be turned into <hi>who</hi> or <hi>which,</hi> otherwiſe it is Demonſtrative; as, <hi>I know that Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a declarative or final Contracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reſolved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A declarative or final Contraction is reſolved by ſupplying the Particle <hi>that,</hi> and turning the Accuſative into the Nom. and the Infinitive into the Verb, and the Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Predicate after a copulative In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitive into the Nominative of the Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate after the copulative Verb.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> Every Infinitive with an Accuſative before it, either expreſt or underſtood, is the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65531:65"/>contraction of a declarative or final Members otherwiſe it is the ſame as the verbal Subſtantive in <hi>ing; as,</hi> to read is profitable, <hi>or</hi> reading is profitable.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Infinitive</hi> to be <hi>often ſuppreſt between the Subject and the Predicate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Infinitive <hi>to be</hi> is often ſuppreſt between the Subject and the Predicate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially after active and paſſive Verbs of calling, making, ſeeming, eſteeming, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſome others; as, <hi>I will make him (to be) a Man; he is eſteemed (to be) honeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Imperative a contraction of a Final Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Imperative is a contraction of a Final Sentence, where the Antecedent Verb is a Verb of commanding or intreating; as, <hi>go thou,</hi> or <hi>I command that thou go; give me Bread,</hi> or <hi>I pray thee give me Bread.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Continuative Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Continuative Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Continuative Sentence is that which hath in it ſome continuative Particle; as, <hi>while, whilſt, when, after that.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> We often ſay <hi>after</hi> by a ſuppreſſion of <hi>that; as,</hi> after I came home.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a continuative Sentence contracted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Continuative Sentence is contracted by putting away the continuative Particle, and turning the Verb into the preſent or preter Participle.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65531:65"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the Nom. in the continuative Member be the ſame with the Nom. in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent Member?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Nom. in the continuative Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (or the Accuſative of the Object which may be turned into the Nom.) be the ſame with the Nom. in the Antecedent Member, then it is put away; as, <hi>when I was Sick I ſtay'd at home,</hi> or <hi>being Sick I ſtay'd at home.</hi> But if it be not the ſame with the Nom. in the Antecedent Member, it is not put away; as, <hi>when my Father was Sick,</hi> or <hi>my Father being Sick, I ſtaid at home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When muſt the Verb be turned into the preſent Participle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Verb muſt be turned into the preſent Participle when the Particle is <hi>while</hi> or <hi>when,</hi> denoting that both actions were done at the ſame time; as, <hi>I ſtood while I was writing my Letter,</hi> or <hi>I ſtood writing my Letter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When muſt the Verb be turn'd into the Preter Participle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Verb muſt be turn'd into the Preter Participle when the continuative Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is <hi>after</hi> or <hi>after that,</hi> denoting that one action was done after another, and then the Participle <hi>having</hi> or <hi>being</hi> is put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Preter Participle in Engliſh; as, <hi>I went home after I had ſaid my Leſſon; having ſaid my Leſſon I went home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not a continuative Member be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65531:66"/>by a verbal Subſtantive of the Action?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Continuative Member may be alſo contracted by the verbal Subſtantive of the Action with the Prepoſition <hi>in,</hi> when both actions are done at the ſame time, or with the Prepoſition <hi>after,</hi> when one action fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the other; as for example, <hi>When</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus <hi>reigned Chriſt was born,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt was born in the reign of</hi> Auguſtus; <hi>The wiſe men came to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>after that Jeſus was born,</hi> or <hi>after the Birth of Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Comparative Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Comparative Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Comparative Sentence is that which hath in it the Comparative Particle <hi>than.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of Compariſon are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are two ſorts of Compariſon, <hi>viz.</hi> a Compariſon of <hi>thing</hi> with <hi>thing,</hi> or a compariſon of <hi>action</hi> with <hi>action.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Compariſon of thing with thing made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Compariſon of <hi>thing</hi> with <hi>thing</hi> is made by a Comparative Adjective be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>than.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Comparative Member contracted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Comparative Member where <hi>thing</hi> is compared with <hi>thing,</hi> is contracted by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the ſubſtantive Verb after <hi>than,</hi> and the Poſitive after the ſubſtantive Verb; as, <hi>I am wiſer than thou art wiſe;</hi> contracted, <hi>I am wiſer than thou.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:65531:66"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>In what caſe is the Subſtantive after</hi> than, <hi>to which the Compariſon is made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſubſtantive after <hi>than,</hi> to which the Compariſon is made, is always the Nom. of the Subject before the ſubſtantive Verb either expreſt or underſtood; and if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Verb come after it, then 'tis a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of a Relative Sentence; as, <hi>I have a better Book than thou haſt,</hi> i. e. <hi>I have a better Book than the Book is which thou haſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What if the Poſitive Adjective to which the compariſon is made, be not the Poſitive of the Comparative Adjective?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If the Poſitive Adjective to which the compariſon is made, be not the Poſitive of the Comparative, it cannot be ſuppreſt nor the Sentence contracted; as, <hi>I am ſtronger than thou art wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Compariſon of Action with Action made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Compariſon of <hi>Action</hi> with <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> is made by a Comparative Adverb be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Particle <hi>than;</hi> and if the Verb af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>than</hi> be the ſame with the Verb in the Antecedent Member, it may be ſuppreſt, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it cannot; as, <hi>I write better than thou writeſt;</hi> contracted, <hi>I write better than thou:</hi> but if I ſay, <hi>I write better than thou readeſt,</hi> it cannot be contracted.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Does not the Particle</hi> than <hi>join like Caſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:65531:67"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No Conjunction joins any Caſe, but always Sentences, tho very often by reaſon of the ſuppreſſion of other words in the Sentence it falls out that the like Caſe is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after the Conjunction, on which the Grammarians falſly grounded a Rule, <hi>That Conjunctions couple like Caſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of an Interrogative Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Interrogative Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Interrogative Sentence is that which has in it ſome Interrogative Adjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or Particle; as, <hi>who, what, whether or no,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is an Interrogative Sentence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Interrogative Sentence is contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by putting away the Interrogative Verb with its Nominative, and putting the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minative in the Subjunctive Member after the Verb; as, <hi>I ask who thou art;</hi> contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>who art thou?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> In a Queſtion made with a Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Verb, the Interrogative Adjective is always the Predicate after it, tho <hi>it</hi> go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; as, <hi>who am I?</hi> but when the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive Verb is in the Imperative, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minative of the Predicate follows the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native of the Subject after it; as, <hi>be thou good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note.</hi> There is no need of a Point of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation after an interrogative Sentence, where the Interrogative Verb is expreſt.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:65531:67"/>
               <head>Of a Disjunctive Sentence.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Disjunctive Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Disjunctive Sentence is that which has in it the Disjunctive Particle <hi>or, either, neither.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Disjunctive Sentence contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Disjunctive Sentence is contracted by ſuppreſſing the Nominative and the Verb in the Subjunctive Member; as, <hi>I have Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or (I have) Goods;</hi> contracted, <hi>I have Money or Goods.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Period.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Period?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Period is a circuit or round of Words wherein the ſenſe is not only perfect, but fully finiſh'd without any following words depending on it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the Members of a Period?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Members of a Period are two compound Sentences, and ſometimes three, rarely four: ſome leſſer Periods conſiſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of one Member, or of one and a half,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65531:68"/>that is of one Compound Sentence, and one ſingle Sentence depending upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Figurative Conſtruction of Words.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Senſe of a Sentence often ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and ambiguous?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Beſides the ambiguity of a ſingle word, by reaſon of its various ſignifications, the ſenſe of a whole Sentence is often liable to be miſtaken by reaſon of the various Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitions, Suppreſſions and Subſtitutions uſed in Engliſh, and all learned Languages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Tranſpoſition.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Tranſpoſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Tranſpoſition</hi> is the placing of words in a Sentence out of the natural order of Conſtruction, that is, in putting words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which ſhould come after, and words after which ſhould go before.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why are words tranſpoſed in a Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Words are tranſpoſed in a Sentence to pleaſe the Ear, by making the contexture of words more harmonious, elegant, and agreeable; for in the natural order it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happens that the pronunciation is very rough and inelegant, becauſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65531:68"/>of rough Conſonants, or of hiant or gaping Vowels, or ſome other harſh conjuncture of words; but where the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral order is ſmooth and grateful to the ear, the words ought not to be tranſpoſed unleſs in Poetry when the neceſſity of the Verſe requires it.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> Many of the Romans too much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting this kind of elegancy, have greatly cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and obſcur'd their ſenſe, as if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd not to be underſtood; or at leaſt to puzzle their Readers with their intricate and perplex'd Contextures.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Suppreſſion, call'd in Greek <hi>Ellipſis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Suppreſſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Suppreſſion</hi> is the omiſſion or leaving out of words in a Sentence that are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to a full Conſtruction; as, <hi>I came from my Father's,</hi> where <hi>Houſe</hi> is ſuppreſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why are words ſuppreſt in a Sentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Words are ſuppreſt in a Sentence for brevity and elegancy.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What words are uſually ſuppreſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It were almoſt infinite to tell all the words that are ſuppreſt in Engliſh, or any other learned Language, only in general you may obſerve theſe three Rules.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1ſt.</hi> That whatever word comes to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in a Sentence oftner than once, it
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:65531:69"/>is ſeldom expreſt but once, to avoid a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of the ſame word which is uſually very inelegant and unpleaſing to the Ear; as for example, <hi>This is my Maſter's Book,</hi> or <hi>this Book is my Maſter's,</hi> for <hi>this Book is my Maſter's Book.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2dly.</hi> Words that are neceſſarily imply'd need not be expreſt; as for Example, <hi>I live in</hi> London, where <hi>Life</hi> is neceſſarily imply'd after the Verb <hi>live,</hi> it having no other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and therefore needleſs to be expreſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>3dly.</hi> Whatever words are uſually ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by the cuſtom of any Language, are not to be expreſt without ſome particular reaſon; as for example, <hi>A good man lives a good Life;</hi> where the Adjective <hi>good</hi> makes it neceſſary to expreſs the Subſtantive <hi>Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p><!-- NOTE -->
                        <hi>Note,</hi> Suppreſſion is the moſt elegant and uſeful of all the figures of Conſtruction, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the tedious and nauſeous repetition of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words that yet are neceſſarily underſtood to make up a full Conſtruction; as for example, <hi>I write a better hand than thou;</hi> where the full Conſtruction amounts to more than double the number of theſe words; thus, <hi>I write a hand, which hand is a better hand, than the hand is good which hand thou writeſt;</hi> which kind of expreſſion is both nauſeous and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:65531:69"/>
               <head>Of Subſtitution, called in Greek <hi>Enallage.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Subſtitution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Subſtitution</hi> is the uſing of one word for another, or one accident of a word for another, as one Caſe for another, one Tenſe for another, one Perſon for another, one Number for another, one Mood for another, and the Primitive and Derivative for one another, Simple and Compound for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the Conſtruction often made accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſenſe, not the words?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Conſtruction is often made according to the ſenſe, not according to the words; that is, not according to the ſubſtituted word, but according to the word for which it is ſubſtituted; as for example, <hi>the whole Nation were called Venetians,</hi> where <hi>the whole Nation</hi> is put <hi>for all the People of the Nation,</hi> to which the Verb Plural <hi>were</hi> is accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated: <hi>part of the men are killed,</hi> where <hi>part</hi> is put for <hi>ſome, ſeveral,</hi> or <hi>many of the men,</hi> to which the Verb Plural <hi>are</hi> is conformed. Thus a concrete Adjective is often ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for its abſtract Subſtantive, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wiſe the Abſtract for the Concrete; as for example, <hi>He has no good in him,</hi> i. e. <hi>no Goodneſs; a man of Knowledg,</hi> for <hi>a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man; a man of Learning,</hi> for <hi>a learned man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:65531:70"/>
               <head>Of Zeugma.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Zeugma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Zeugma</hi> is when two or more Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in a Sentence have ſome words common to them, eſpecially Verbs or Adjectives, and ſome words peculiar to each of them; then the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantives with what is common to them, are firſt expreſt, and then what is peculiar to each is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined by a Suppreſſion of what is common; as for example, <hi>One Brother was kill'd in</hi> Flanders, <hi>and another in</hi> France; contracted, <hi>The two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were kill'd, one in</hi> Flanders, <hi>the other in</hi> France.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Soleciſm and Pleonaſm.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Soleciſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Soleciſm</hi> is when words are joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary to the laws of Grammar, as <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks,</hi> for <hi>I think.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Pleonaſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Pleonaſm</hi> is the uſing of unneceſſary words in a Sentence, eſpecially Nouns and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles; as, <hi>he ſpoke with his Mouth; he ſaw with his Eyes; he heard with his Ears:</hi> where the words <hi>Mouth, Eyes, Ears,</hi> are ſuperfluous in the Sentence, becauſe they are neceſſarily imply'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the natural Order of words.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Since the Compoſition of Sentences are often intricate and obſcure, how may the ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them be beſt found?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The beſt way to find the true ſenſe and meaning of any Sentence, is to reduce tranſpos'd
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:65531:70"/>words to the Natural Order, to ſupply ſuppreſt words, and to change ſubſtituted words into the words for which they are ſubſtituted, and laſtly to diſtinguiſh ambiguous words.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Natural Order of words?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Natural or Grammatical Order is that depending words follow the words on which they depend, except Relatives and Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, whoſe Natural Order is to come before the words of which they are governed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may every Sentence be divided?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every Sentence may be divided into two parts, the <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Predicate:</hi> the Nom. of the Subject with all that depends upon it, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately or immediately, is the Subject of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and muſt be taken firſt: the Verb with all that depends upon it, mediately or immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, is the Predicate of the Sentence, and muſt be taken next; as in the following Example, Alexander <hi>the Great, Son of</hi> Philip <hi>King of</hi> Macedonia (the ſubject) <hi>conquered the greateſt part of the World, in the ſpace of twelve years,</hi> (the Predicate).</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may one reduce words to the Natural Order?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Words may be reduced to the natural Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thus: firſt read the Sentence deliberately to a full ſtop. Look next for the Verb, that by the Number and Perſon of the Verb you may find out the Nom. Caſe; and if there be two Verbs in the Sentence, the firſt is to be taken firſt, unleſs it be the Infinitive, or have a Relative or a Conjunction before it; for in Compound Sentences the Subjunctive Member follows the Antecedent Member in the natural Order.</p>
               <p>The Relative and its Member muſt come im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:65531:71"/>after the Antecedent Subſtantive. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs and Prepoſitions come after their Verbs and Participles. The Adjective in Engliſh comes before its Subſtantive; but if any other word depend upon the Adjective, then it muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily come after the Subſtantive to avoid confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſenſe; as for example, <hi>I ſaw</hi> Peter <hi>writing a Letter,</hi> not <hi>I ſaw writing</hi> Peter <hi>a Letter.</hi> Reſolve <hi>s</hi> or <hi>es</hi> Poſſeſſive into its Primitive Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive made by <hi>of:</hi> dilate all contracted Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by which you may find the true Grammar of the words, and conſequently the true ſenſe of the Sentence.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note, <hi>Conjunctions and Conjunctive Adjectives do always belong to the Sentence immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; and if they be not in the middle by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Antecedent Member before;</hi> as, <hi>If thou be rich thou ſhalt have many Friends,</hi> or <hi>thou ſhalt have many Friends if thou be rich.</hi> If there be a Voc. Caſe, it muſt be taken firſt, becauſe it is the Perſon to whom the following Speech is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt. If there be any Interjections or other exciting Particles, they are next in order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe they excite the attention of the hearers to what follows.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Points, Pauſes or Stops.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many Points or Stops are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are four Points or Stops, a <hi>Comma</hi> (,) a <hi>Colon</hi> (:) <hi>Semi-Colon</hi> (;) and a <hi>Period</hi> or full ſtop (.)</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the uſe of the Points?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The uſe of the Points is to give time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration or Breathing, and to avoid the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſenſe in joining words together in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65531:71"/>ſpeaking or reading, which are not joined in Senſe or Conſtruction.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is a Comma put?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Comma</hi> is put between the Members of a Compound Sentence, whether full or contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and between all words that have not an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate dependence upon one another in Senſe and Conſtruction.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is a Colon put?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Colon</hi> or Member is put between the two Members of a Period, or which is the ſame, between two compound Sentences.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is a Semi-Colon put?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Semi-Colon</hi> or half Member is put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a whole Member and a half Member, that is between a compound Sentence, and a ſingle Sentence following it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is a Period put?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>Period</hi> or full Stop is put at the end of a Sentence containing full and compleat Senſe, and where no other words following have any dependence upon it.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->Note, <hi>A</hi> Comma <hi>is the ſhorteſt Stop, a</hi> Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colon <hi>is longer than a</hi> Comma; <hi>a</hi> Colon <hi>is longer than a</hi> Semicolon; <hi>a</hi> Period <hi>is longeſt of all; as in the following Period.</hi> Riches are often joined with habitual Vices in the Poſſeſſors, and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently ſerve for bad or good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes: the greedy purſuit of them, blaſts all true worth of Spirit, and turns the Soul to Earth and Corruption.<!-- /NOTE --></p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Note of Interrogation. (?)</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is a Note of Interrogation put?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Note of Interrogation is put after a ſhort and contracted Queſtion, to ſhow that it
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:65531:72"/>is a Queſtion; but if the Interrogative Verb be expreſs'd, there's no need of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Note of Admiration. (!)</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is a Note of Admiration put?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Note of Admiration is put after words, to ſhow how wonderful, ſtrange, or deplorable the Thing is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Parentheſis. ()</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the uſe of a Parentheſis?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The uſe of a <hi>Parentheſis</hi> is to incloſe words put within a Sentence, which are no part of it, and without which the ſenſe is perfect.</p>
               <p><!-- NOTE -->
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The mark of an Apoſtroph is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times put before <hi>s</hi> ſervile, not becauſe there is any Vowel omitted, but to ſhew that <hi>s</hi> there is an additional Termination, and not a part of the Theam or Primitive word: this mark does not ſeem neceſſary but when <hi>s</hi> ſervile is added to a foreign word uſed in Engliſh without any alteration; as, <hi>great Encomium</hi>'s, <hi>two Comma</hi>'s; or when a word is taken materially, that is, for the Letters and Syllables, or (which is the ſame) for the Sound without the Signification; as, <hi>yea's</hi> and <hi>no's; if's</hi> or <hi>and's.</hi>
                  <!-- /NOTE -->
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:65531:72"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
